<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wicked life and wofull death of Herod the Great a stranger by nation yet by the Romans made king of the Jews : taking in also the story of the Jews during all the time of his reign ... / by Sa. Clarke.</title>
            <author>Clarke, Samuel, 1599-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4560</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23712</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07880668</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07880668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1202:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wicked life and wofull death of Herod the Great a stranger by nation yet by the Romans made king of the Jews : taking in also the story of the Jews during all the time of his reign ... / by Sa. Clarke.</title>
                  <author>Clarke, Samuel, 1599-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Miller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Herod --  I, --  King of Judea, 73-4 B.C.</term>
               <term>Jews --  History --  168 B.C.-135 A.D.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40260:1"/>
            <p>THE WICKED LIFE, AND WOFULL DEATH OF HEROD the Great, A ſtranger by Nation, yet by the <hi>Romans</hi> made <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Taking in alſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Jews</hi> during all the time of his Reign, which was about 37 years: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thirty five were before the Incarnation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and two after.</p>
            <p>Whereby much light is given to many paſſages in the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts: and at which time that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of old <hi>Jaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was fulfilled: <q>
                  <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, till Shilo come.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Gen. 49.10.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſometime Paſtor in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The memory of the Juſt is bleſſed: but the name of the wicked ſhall rot. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 10.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Miller</hi> at the Sign of the Gilded-Acron in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard near the little North door. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:40260:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh. Hall <hi>R.P.D.</hi> Epiſc. Lond. à Sac. Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb. 18. 1663.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40260:2"/>
            <head>THE WICKED LIFE, AND WOFULL DEATH OF HEROD, the Great, In whoſe Time our LORD CHRIST was Born.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EROD,</hi> ſirnamed the <hi>Great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree.</note> was the Son of <hi>Antipas,</hi> or <hi>Antipater,</hi> an <hi>Idumaean,</hi> a prime man both for birth, and wealth amongſt them: His mothers name was <hi>Cyprus,</hi> born at an eminent place amongſt the <hi>Arabians,</hi> ſo that when this <hi>Herod</hi> acquired the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Judea,</hi> that Propheſie of old <hi>Jacob</hi> was fulfilled, Gen. 49.10. <hi>The ſcepter ſhall not depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>nor a Law-giver from between his feet, until</hi> Shiloh <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Antipater,</hi> riding his circuit about the Province of <hi>Judea,</hi> whereof <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> had made him Governour, repreſſed them who were deſirous of innovation, both by threats, and counſell; telling them, that if they would be content with their Prince <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> (whom <hi>Caeſar</hi> alſo had confirmed in the High-Prieſthood) they might live happily in their own <hi>poſſeſſions:</hi> but if they promiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves new hopes, and thought that they ſhould gain much by innovations, they ſhould have him a Maſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Governour, and <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> a Tyrant inſtead of a King: and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> bitter enemies inſtead of Princes; for that they would by no means ſuffer any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40260:3"/> thing to be altered, from what they had ſettled. But <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater</hi> perceiving <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> to be dull, and idle, he ſettled the ſtate of the Province as himſelf pleaſed, making his elder ſon, <hi>Phaſaelus,</hi> Governour of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Countries adjoyning: and to <hi>Herod</hi> his ſecond ſon, being then a very young man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> is made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Galilee.</hi>
               </note> he committed the care of <hi>Galilee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being <hi>Praefect</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> there was one <hi>Eſekias,</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> who aſſociating to himſelf many other lewd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, exerciſed thievery, and uſed to make incurſions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Syria</hi> in Troops: Theſe <hi>Herod</hi> purſued, and having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Eſekias,</hi> he put him to Death, <note place="margin">He puts <hi>Eſekias</hi> to death.</note>which fact of his gat him much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vour with the <hi>Syrians,</hi> which Province alſo was then und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r his Government.</p>
            <p>The violence, and bold nature of <hi>Herod,</hi> who was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of the Tyranny, much terrified the Princes of the <hi>Jews,</hi> wherefore they addreſſed themſelves to <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> accuſed <hi>Antipater;</hi> but eſpecially they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of <hi>Herod</hi> for that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had put to Death <hi>Eſekias,</hi> with many others, without any Commiſſion from <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> in contempt of their Laws, by which, no man ought to ſuffer, though never ſo wicked, unleſs he were firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Judges. The Mothers alſo of them that were killed, ceaſed not daily in the Temple to weary both the King and the people with their continuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, deſiring that <hi>Herod</hi> might be made to give an account of theſe his doings before the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi>
               <note place="margin">He is ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim.</hi>
               </note> whereupon <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> moved herewith commanded <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod</hi> to be called before the Councell, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to plead his own cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having ordered the affairs of <hi>Galilee</hi> as he thought beſt for his own advantage, being forewarned by his Father that he ſhould not come into the Councell as a Private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he took with him a moderate, but yet a ſufficient Guard: not too great, leaſt he ſhould terrifie <hi>Hyrc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus,</hi> nor too little, leſt he ſhould expoſe him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lf to danger from the Judgement. When <hi>Herod</hi> therefore preſented himſelf before the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> in his royall robes,<note place="margin">Appears with a Guard.</note> and his Guard in armes, they were all aſtoniſhed, neither durſt any one of them that accuſed him in his abſence, now
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40260:3"/> ſpeak a word againſt him; but all of them kept ſilence, not knowing what to do. Then one of the Councell, called <hi>Sameas,</hi> a juſt man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sameas</hi> his boldneſs.</note> being not at all diſtracted with fear, roſe up, and not only accuſed <hi>Herod</hi> of preſumption and violence, but laid the fault upon the Judges, and King himſelf who had granted him ſo great a liberty, and told them, that afterwards,<note place="margin">A predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> by the juſt Judgement of God they ſhould be puniſhed by <hi>Herod</hi> himſelf; and the event made him a true Prophet. For the Judges of that Councel, and <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> himſelf were afterwards put to death by <hi>Herod</hi> when he came to be King. But <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> perceiving that the Judges were inclining to paſs ſentence of Death upon <hi>Herod,</hi> put off the buſineſs till the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt day, and privately adviſed him to ſhift for himſelf, and ſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> as if he fled from the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> flies</note> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf before <hi>Sextus Caeſar,</hi> and having ſecured his own affairs, he profeſſed openly,<note place="margin">Refuſed to appear when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain cited</note> that if he were again ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Judges he would not appear, which they took in great diſdain, and endeavoured to perſwade <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> that all theſe things tended to his deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> to increaſe his power, gave a great ſumme of money to <hi>Sextus Caeſar,</hi> who thereupon made him Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Caeloſyria:</hi> He,<note place="margin">Is made Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Caeloſyria.</hi>
               </note> being elated with this advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and taking it impatiently that he had been called before the Councel, raiſed an Army, and went againſt <hi>Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>canus:</hi> But his Father <hi>Antipater,</hi> and Brother <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> meeting him, by their intreaties prevailed that he ſhould not go againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but be content to have affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, adding that it would be diſhonourable for him if he ſhould attempt any thing further againſt him that had advanced him to his dignity; hereupon he deſiſted, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſufficient for his future hopes that he had ſhewed to that Nation of what power he was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſius</hi> and <hi>Marcus,</hi> two <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man</hi> Generals, coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Syria,</hi> after the death of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in it.</note> confirmed <hi>Herod</hi> in his Government of <hi>Caeloſyria,</hi> and delivered to him great forces both of horſe and foot, and ſhips at Sea, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him alſo the Kingdome of <hi>Judea,</hi> after the war
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40260:4"/> ſhould be ended which they were waging with <hi>M. Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and young <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Antipater</hi> (the Father of <hi>Herod</hi>) was Feaſted at <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> his houſe, at which time, one <hi>Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> corrupting the Kings Butler, poyſoned <hi>Antipater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> poiſoned.</note> and preſently raiſing a band of Souldiers, ſeized upon the Governmen of the City of <hi>Jeruſalem. Phaſaelus</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> being grievouſly offended hereat, charged <hi>Malichus</hi> with their Fathers death, which he ſtifly denied: But <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> had a great mind preſently to revenge the murther, and to raiſe an Army for that purpoſe, had not <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> interpoſed, who ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ged it more meet to circumvent <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lichus</hi> by Policy, leaſt they ſhould ſeem to be the beginners of a civil war, and accordingly <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aelus</hi> made as though he accepted of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lichus</hi> his juſtification, and believed that he was not guilty of his Fathers Death, and ſo buſied himſelf in building a ſtately Monument for him.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Herod</hi> coming to <hi>Samaria,</hi> and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in a deſperate eſtate by reaſon of their Civil diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he appeaſed the diſcords amongſt the Inhabitants and reſtored it to peace: and not long after, the Feaſt of <hi>Penticoſt</hi> approaching,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> goes to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               </note> he went to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> accompanied with ſome ſouldiers, of whom <hi>Malichus</hi> being affraid, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> not to ſuffer him to enter, which <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> accordingly did, alleadging that amongſt the holy People that came to the Feaſt, it was not lawfull to bring in a mixt multitude of prophane men. But <hi>Herod</hi> making ſmall account of the prohibition, entred the City by night, and thereby mightily terrified <hi>Malichus;</hi> who, thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to his wonted diſſimulations, openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed with tears the Death of <hi>Antipater,</hi> as of his dear Friend: And it was judged meet by <hi>Herods</hi> Friends, that he ſhould take no notice of this diſſimulation, but courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly again intertain <hi>Malichus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to revenge his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death.</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> by letters certified <hi>Caſſius</hi> of his Fathers death, who very well knowing the temper of <hi>Malichus,</hi> wrote back unto <hi>Herod</hi> to revenge the ſame, and ſecretly alſo gave order to the Tribunes that were at <hi>Tyre</hi> to be aiding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40260:4"/> to <hi>Herod</hi> in his ſo juſt undertaking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſſius</hi> afterward having taken the City of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours came from every place, bringing Crowns and Preſents, to him: and here <hi>Herod,</hi> expecting that <hi>Malichus</hi> ſhould doe the like, intended to have him puniſhed for the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Father: But <hi>Malichus</hi> had another deſign on foot, purpoſing, that whileſt <hi>Caſſius</hi> was buſie in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the warre againſt <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> to ſtir up the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> to revolt from the <hi>Romans,</hi> and to depoſe <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> and get the Kingdome to himſelf; But <hi>Herod</hi> being Politick and underſtanding of the treachery, invited him and <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> with ſome other of their companions to ſupper: At which time he ſent one of his ſervants, under pretence of providing for the Banquet, whereas indeed he ſent him to the Tribunes to deſire them to ſet upon <hi>Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> with their weapons, who being mindfull of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>Caſſius,</hi> finding <hi>Malichus,</hi> they ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m through, and ſlew him, at which <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> being aſtoniſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malchus</hi> ſlain.</note> fell into a ſwoun, and being ſcarcely come to himſelf, he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who had ſlain <hi>Malichus,</hi> and when one of the Tribunes anſwered that it was done by the command of <hi>Caſſius,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Truly</hi> Caſſius <hi>hath preſerved me and my Country, in kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him who was a Traitor to both;</hi> but whether herein he ſpake as he thought, or that through fear only he ſeemed to approve the fact, is uncertain.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Caſſius</hi> was gon out of <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſedition at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
               </note> there aroſe a ſedition at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> For <hi>Paelix,</hi> who was left there by <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſius</hi> with ſouldiers, in revenge of the death of <hi>Malichus,</hi> ſet upon <hi>Phaſaelus,</hi> and the people betook themſelves to their Armes. At which time <hi>Herod</hi> was with <hi>Fabius,</hi> the Governour of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and had a mind to help his Brother, but was hindered by a ſudden ſickneſs: Yet did <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> get the better of <hi>Faelix,</hi> forcing him into the Town, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards agreeing upon quarter, ſuffered him to go out: But he was very angry with <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> that after the receipt of ſo many favours from him, he yet favoured <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elix,</hi> and ſuffered the Brother of <hi>Malichus</hi> to ſeize upon ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and amongſt the reſt, of the Caſtle of <hi>Maſſada,</hi> which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40260:5"/> was a moſt ſtrong piece.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Valour.</note>As ſoone as <hi>Herod</hi> was recovered, he went againſt the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Malichus,</hi> and took from him all the Caſtles that he had ſeized upon, and <hi>Maſsada</hi> alſo, where he took him Priſoner, yet afterwards ſet him at liberty upon compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He alſo recovered three Caſtles that were ſeized upon by <hi>Maſion,</hi> the Tyrant of the <hi>Tyrians</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> but gave Quarter to all the Souldiers, and ſent them home well rewarded, by which means he procured the love of the Citizens,<note place="margin">His Policy</note> but he greater hatred of the Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Shortly after <hi>Antigonus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> Brother to <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> invaded <hi>Judaea,</hi> being aſſiſted by <hi>Ptolomei,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Menaeus,</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> the Governor of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and <hi>Maſion,</hi> the Tyrant of the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> who adhered to him for the hatred that he bore to <hi>Herod,</hi> whom <hi>Herod</hi> meeting, when they had ſcarce entred the borders of <hi>Judea,</hi> overcame t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in Battell,<note place="margin">He over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus.</hi>
               </note> and drave them thence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> honoured him with Crowns, as ſoone as he returned to <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> For he was already accounted as one of the Family of <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> being to marry <hi>Mariamn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Mary,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> the Brother of <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and of <hi>Alexandra,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Hyrcanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Anthony</hi> having overcome <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> there met him Ambaſſies from all Nations in <hi>Bythinia,</hi> and amongſt the reſt, ſome of the Rulers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to accuſe <hi>Phaſaelus,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> alleadging that <hi>Hircanus</hi> ruled only in ſhew, but in truth, all the power was in the two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Yet <hi>Anthony</hi> highly honoured <hi>Herod,</hi> who was come thither to wipe off all thoſe objections, whereby it came to paſſe that his adverſaries were not ſo much as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſpeak with <hi>Anthony:</hi> and this <hi>Herod</hi> had obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Bribes.</p>
            <p>Yet not long after there came an hundred of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>Daphne,</hi> near <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> to <hi>Anthony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed to <hi>Anthony.</hi>
               </note> to accuſe <hi>Phaeſaelus</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> having choſen out of their whole number the moſt Eloquent, to mannage their buſineſs: But <hi>Meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la</hi> undertook the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40260:5"/> of the two Brothers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed to <hi>Anthony.</hi>
               </note> with whom alſo <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who had betrothed his Grand-daughter to <hi>Herod.</hi> Both parties being heard, <hi>Anthony</hi> asked <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> whether of the two parties were fitteſt to Govern a Commonwealth? who ſpeaking for the young men,<note place="margin">But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted.</note> 
               <hi>Anthony</hi> that loved them for their Fathers ſake, his old Friend, he made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem both <hi>Tetraerchs,</hi> leaving to them the Government of all <hi>Judaea,</hi> writing his letters to the ſame purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, and clapped fifteen of their Adverſaries into priſon, and would have put them to death, had not <hi>Herod</hi> intreated for them. But when the People did nothing but ran upon <hi>Herod, Anthony</hi> in diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſlew them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus</hi> the Son of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bulus</hi> hired the <hi>Parthians</hi> to tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ate the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome from <hi>Hyrc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus</hi> to himſelf and to kill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, who c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ming along with him, and ſome <hi>Jews</hi> alſo joining themſelves to him, he came to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and they ſet upon the Kings Houſe:<note place="margin">War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi> and <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note> But <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> defended it againſt them; and in the Market place, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming them in a fight, forced them to fly into the Temple, where they ſhut them in, and placed ſixty men in ſome adjoyning houſes to prevent their flight: but the people having the two Brethren ſet fire on thoſe Houſes, and burnt the men in them, which ſo enraged <hi>Herod</hi> that he ſlew many of the people: and each laying wait for the other, ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry day ſome were murdered.</p>
            <p>The day of <hi>Pent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> being come, many thouſands of men, as well armed as unarmed gathered together about the Temple from all parts of the Country,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> prevails.</note> and ſeized upon the Temple, and City, all but the Kings Houſe, which <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> kept w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a few ſouldiers, as <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelus</hi> did the walls. Theſe brothers aſſiſting each other, aſſaulted their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in the ſuburbs forced many thouſands of them to fly, ſome into the City, and ſome into the Temple, and others into a rampire that was near the City.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Antigonus</hi> deſired that <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c rus,</hi> the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erall of the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thians</hi> might be admitted to make peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them:<note place="margin">The <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thians</hi> falſhood.</note> which <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> aſſented to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Pacorus</hi> perſwaded him to go with him as an Ambaſſador to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zapharnes</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40260:6"/> (an other Generall of the <hi>Parthians</hi>) laying an ambuſh for him by the way: <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> aſſented, though much againſt the mind of his Brother <hi>Herod,</hi> and was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go with <hi>Pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and took <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> along with him. <hi>Pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> leaving two hundred Horſemen with <hi>Herod,</hi> and ten whom they called <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utheri,</hi> went along with the Ambaſſadors. And as ſoone as they were come into <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile, Barzapharnes</hi> entertained them with a cheerefull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and beſtowed gifts upon them, but watched an opportunity to intrap them: and ſo <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> was brought with his company to a place near the Sea ſide called <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dippon;</hi> where <hi>Ophellus,</hi> a rich <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> underſtanding of the treachery intended againſt them, offered <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> ſome ſhips to carry him away: But he unwilling to leave <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in danger, expoſtulated with <hi>Barzapharnes</hi> about the injury offered to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m who were Ambaſſadors, who ſwore that theſe thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were not true, and preſently went to <hi>Pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſooner was he gon, but <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were clapped up in Priſon, much deteſting the perf diouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Parthians:</hi> and an Eunuch alſo was ſent to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> with a command to ſurprize him if he could get him out of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> flies from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> having intelligence what had happened to his Brother, taking with him ſuch forces as he had in readineſs, and his Mother <hi>Cybele,</hi> his ſiſter <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome,</hi> his wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> and his wives Mother <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and his youngeſt Brother <hi>Pheroras,</hi> with their ſervants, he privately by night took his flight into <hi>Idumaea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In their journey, his Mother, by the overthrow of her Coach, was in great danger of death, and <hi>Herod,</hi> fearing leaſt the enemies ſhould overtake them whileſt they ſtayed there, drew forth his ſword, thinking to kill himſelf:<note place="margin">He would have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> But being reſtrained by thoſe which ſtood by, he went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Maſſada,</hi> a very ſtrong place, which is ſeated in <hi>Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> by the neareſt way that he could poſſible: The <hi>Parthians</hi> firſt, and alſo the <hi>Jews</hi> purſuing him by that he was ſixty furlongs from the City, but he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40260:6"/> repelled them both in fight.</p>
            <p>The next day after <hi>Herod</hi> had fled from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Parthians</hi> plundered the City, and the Kings houſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> only the Treaſure of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> which was three hundred Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, remained untouched. A great part alſo of <hi>Herods</hi> ſubſtance which he had not carried away with him, they ſiezed upon; and not ſatisfied therewith, they har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed all the the Country alſo, and raſed the rich City of <hi>Mariſſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antig nus</hi> being thus ſettled in <hi>Judaea</hi> by the <hi>Parthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antigonus</hi> made King of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </note> he received into his Cuſtody <hi>Hy canus,</hi> and <hi>Phaſae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> who were priſoners: yet he was much grieved that the women were got away, whom he had intended to deliver to the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> tog ther with the money which he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to gave them. Being afraid alſo leaſt <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> ſhould ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the favour of the people be reſtored to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Prieſthood, he cut off his eares,<note place="margin">Cuts off <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> ears.</note> thereby ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering him unfit for the Prieſthood, the Law forbiding that any one who wanted a member ſhould approach to the Altar. <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.17, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> knowing that his death was determined,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> kills him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> ſought to lay violent hands upon himſelf, but being hindred by reaſon of his chains, he daſhed out his brains againſt a ſtone: Yet before he was quite dead, hearing by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that his Brother <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> was eſcaped, he greatly rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that there was one left to revenge his death. The <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> though they miſſed of the women, which they moſt of all deſired, yet having ſettled all things at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> with <hi>Antigonus,</hi> when they departed, took <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> along with them Priſoner into <hi>Parthia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> not hearing of his Brother <hi>Phaſaelus</hi> his death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> flees to <hi>Malchus</hi> King of <hi>Arabia.</hi>
               </note> went to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lchus,</hi> the King of the <hi>Arabians [Nabathaeans]</hi> who were obliged to him by many favours he had done them, purpoſing ſo ſoone as poſſiblely he could to redeem his Brother for three hundred Talents from the enemy: For which cauſe he carried along with him young <hi>Phaſaelus,</hi> his Brothers Son, about ſeven years old, to leave him for a pledge with the <hi>Arabians:</hi> But there met him ſome that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40260:7"/> were ſent from <hi>Malchus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Is rejected by him.</note> to command him to depart from the bounds of his Kingdome, for ſo the <hi>Parthians</hi> had required: Yet he pretended that he did it by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of his Noble men, purpoſing to cozen him of that great treaſure which his Father <hi>Antipater</hi> had committed to his truſt. <hi>Herod</hi> taking this very heavily, turned aſide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a certain Temple, where he had left many of his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but the next day, when he came to <hi>Rhinocorura</hi> he heard of his Brothers death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malchus,</hi> upon ſecond thoughts, repenting of his ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, ſent in all haſt after <hi>Herod:</hi> but the meſſengers could not overtake him: for he was gon farre on his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards <hi>Peluſium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> goes into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
               </note> where the Marriners that were ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> refuſed to take him in. There, by the Magiſtrates of the City he was honourably intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and brought to <hi>Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>patra,</hi> the Queen, who could not prevail with him to ſtay at that time, becauſe he was haſtening to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">From thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </note> though the ſea was very tempeſtuous, and as then the affairs in <hi>Italy</hi> were in no very good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As he ſailed from <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>exandria</hi> towards <hi>Phamphilia</hi> he met with a very great ſtorm, which made him caſt overboard much of his ſubſtance, and ſcarcely got he to <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He comes to <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
               </note>At <hi>Rhodes</hi> two of his greateſt friends met him, <hi>Sappinas,</hi> and <hi>Ptolomaeus,</hi> and finding that the City had ſuffered much in the warre againſt <hi>Caſſius,</hi> he could not be reſtrained, no not by his preſent poverty, but that he would do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it, even beyond his ability: After which he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Frigot to be built, and embarking himſelf with his Friends in it,<note place="margin">So into <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </note> he arrived at <hi>Brunduſium</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and from thence went to <hi>Rome,</hi> declaring unto <hi>M. Anthony</hi> thoſe things that had happened to himſelf and his Family, and that thorough many tempeſts, and dangers he had retired unto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anthony</hi> favours him.</note> as his onely refuge, in whom all his hope lay.</p>
            <p>This Narration moved compaſſion in <hi>Anthony;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring alſo his Fathers friendſhip towards him, but that which prevailed moſt, was the promiſe of a great ſum of mony if he would help him to the Kingdome: <hi>Anthony</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40260:7"/> alſo hated <hi>Antigonus</hi> as a man of a turbulent ſpirit, and an enemy to the <hi>Romans. Caeſar</hi>
               <note place="margin">And <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>
               </note> alſo partly for that <hi>Antipater [Herods</hi> Father] had been fellow ſouldier with his Father in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and for other curteſies which he had ſhewed him, and partly to gratifie <hi>Anthony,</hi> whom he ſaw to be well affected to <hi>Herod,</hi> was willing to promote his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: whereupon the Senate being aſſembled, <hi>Meſſala,</hi> and <hi>Atpatinus,</hi> brought in <hi>Herod,</hi> and after they had praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, reckoning up the love, and ſervices that both he, and his Father had done for the <hi>Romans,</hi> and accuſing <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi> both for former crimes, and for that newly he had received the Kingdome of the <hi>Jews</hi> from the <hi>Parthians</hi> in contempt of the <hi>Romans:</hi> and when <hi>Anthony</hi> alſo had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the Senate how much conducing it was to the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rthian</hi> warre, then in hand, that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould be made King: <hi>Antigonus</hi> was declared an enemy,<note place="margin">The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate make him King.</note> and the Kingly Title was devolved upon <hi>Herod</hi> by their genearll ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage.</p>
            <p>Whileſt theſe things were tranſacting at <hi>Rome, Ventidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Generall eaſiely recovered <hi>Paleſtine, Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the King thereof, being much afraid of him, and he exacted great ſums of mony from all men, but eſpecially from <hi>Antigonus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</note> who in <hi>Herods</hi> abſence had beſieged his Family in <hi>Maſsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> which place, though it abounded with all other kinds of proviſion, yet it wanted water, ſo that <hi>Joſeph, Herods</hi> Brother, who commanded in chief there, with two hundred of his friends intended to fly to the <hi>Arabians;</hi> for that he heard that <hi>Malchus</hi> now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him of his former ingratitude towards <hi>Herod:</hi> But the very night a great ſhore of rain falling filled their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns, which made him chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his purpoſe,<note place="margin">A ſpecial provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> and the next morning, making a ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lant ſalley forth, they killed many of <hi>Antigonus</hi> his men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ventidius</hi> encamped near to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and drew from <hi>Antigonus</hi> a ſufficient ſum of money, and to the intent that his fraudulent dealing ſhould not be diſcovered, he left one <hi>Silo</hi> there, with part of his forces, under a pretence of helping <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who alſo was to be feed by <hi>Antigonus,</hi> leſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40260:8"/> he ſhould raiſe him ſome new troubles; which <hi>Antigonus</hi> ſubmitted to, hoping that the <hi>Parthians</hi> would ſhortly come to his aid.</p>
            <p>After the Senate was diſmiſſed, <hi>Anthony,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> went out, leading <hi>Herod</hi> betwe n them, who was alſo accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the Conſuls, and other Magiſtrates, and ſo they went all together up into the <hi>Cap t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> to ſacrifice to the Gods, and to place there the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the Senate: and the new King, the firſt day of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was Feaſted by <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> and within ſeven d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was by <hi>Anthony</hi> diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of <hi>It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> honoured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>xpected felicity.</p>
            <p>Shortly after <hi>Anthon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being to go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Parthian</hi> War, had all his Acts, as well paſt as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, confirmed by the Senate, whereupon he ſent to ſome Kings by his own au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to pay certain Tribute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Kingdom enlarged.</note> and he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Herod</hi> King both of the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being returned out of <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Pt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ais,</hi> quickly gathered ſtore of Souldiers, both of ſuch as he hired, as alſo of his own Countrymen, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling through <hi>Galile</hi> againſt <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus:</hi> being aided by <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dius,</hi> who were comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to conduct him into his Kin dom; and as he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt on, his forces daily increaſed, and all <hi>Galile,</hi> except a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew, fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with him.</p>
            <p>As <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was marching towards <hi>Maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> where he was neceſſarily to relieve hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kindred, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppi</hi> would not let him paſs, wherefore he was to reduce it, leſt he ſhould leave ſo ſtrong a place behind him in his paſſage to <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> which occaſion <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> taking hold on (for he was not yet come to <hi>H ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) diſlodged hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Army from about <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whom the <hi>Jews</hi> pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Herod <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves</hi> Silo.</note> but <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> meeting him with a ſmall party ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought very cowar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly.</p>
            <p>After he had taken <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He takes <hi>Joppa.</hi>
               </note> he haſted to <hi>Maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>da</hi> to raiſe the ſiege, and his Army encreaſed dayly, many of the Country people joyning with him: and having relieved his friends in <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beſieges <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </note> he haſted towards <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and though <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> had laid ambuſhments for him in divers places, yet he drew near to the City, <hi>Silo</hi> following and the <hi>Jews</hi> being terrified with his power. When he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40260:8"/> on the Weſt ſide of the City, they upon the walls ſhot at him with darts and arrowes: others alſo ſallying out in Troops, beat up ſome of his quarters. Then did <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> by an Herald proclaim round about the Walls, that he came for the publick good, and to preſerve the City from ruine, and withall, he promiſed pardon for all former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctings. On the other ſide <hi>Antigonus,</hi> directing his ſpeech to <hi>Silo,</hi> and the <hi>Romans,</hi> told them, that it was unjuſtly done of the Senate to give the Kingdom to <hi>Herod,</hi> a private man, and an <hi>Idumae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and ſo but an half-Jew, whereas by cuſtom it was to be given to one of the High-Prieſts line. His men alſo ſhooting valiantly from the Towers, drave the enemy from the walls: and <hi>Silo</hi> (who was beforehand bribed by <hi>Antigonus</hi>) ſuborned ſome of his Souldiers to demand of <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> more proviſions, and larger pay, and to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn into commodious winter-quarters. The Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus troubled, and begining to diſlodg, <hi>Herod</hi> intreated the Captains, and Souldiers of <hi>Silo</hi>'s Army, that they would not now forſake him, he being ſent both by <hi>Anthony, Caeſar,</hi> and the Senate, to take poſſeſſion of the Kingdom; and withall he ſent into all the Country, and brought in ſuch ſtore of proviſions, that there was no occaſion for <hi>Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and his Army to complain. He commanded his Friends alſo that inhabited about <hi>Samaria,</hi> that they ſhould bring to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo</hi> Corn, Wine, Oyl, Cattle, and other neceſſaries, that the Souldiers for the future might have plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antigonus</hi> having intelligence hereof, ſent forth ſome to intercept the victualers: but <hi>Herod</hi> taking with him ſome Cohorts, <hi>viz.</hi> five of the <hi>R mans,</hi> and as many of the <hi>Jews,</hi> with ſome forreign Souldiers, and a few Horſe mixed with them,<note place="margin">Herod <hi>takes</hi> Jericho.</note> flew out to <hi>Jeric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and found the City forſaken of the Inhabitants, and five hundred Families of them were fled to the tops of the Hills, whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> took, and diſmiſſed in ſafety: But the <hi>Romans</hi> entring the City, plundered it, where they found all ſorts of preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> movables. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> leaving a Garriſon there, returned to his Camp before <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and then diſmiſſed the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſending them into winter-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Idumaea, Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Galile,</hi> which Countries were
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40260:9"/> lately ſurrendred to them: But <hi>Antigonus</hi> by bribes obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Silo,</hi> that part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Army ſhould be quartered in <hi>Lyáda,</hi> currying thereby favour with <hi>Anthony:</hi> and thus the <hi>Romans</hi> lived in plenty, and without bearing Arms.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>But <hi>Herod</hi> could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le: For ſending his Brother <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a thouſand Foot, and four hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ia,</hi> and there ſetled his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſt of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, whom he had drawn out of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Then did he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rch into <hi>Galile,</hi> where he ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſome places which were yet held by <hi>Antigonus</hi> his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons: and when he came to <hi>Seph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eus</hi> in ſnowie weather, <hi>Antigonus</hi> his men fled away and there be found great ſtore of neceſſaries. From thence he ſent a Troop of Horſe, and three Companies of Foot againſt ſome Thieves that dwelt in Caves,<note place="margin">He pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues the Thieves.</note> not far from the Village <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> by which means he kept them from doing miſchief. Then he march<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with his whole Army, whom the enemy met, and encountred reſolutely, in ſo much as <hi>Herods</hi> left wing began to waver, till himſelf coming on with the main bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, encouraged his own men to ſtand their ground, and cauſed the enemy to flee, whom he followed as far as <hi>Jordan:</hi> by which victory he brought all <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lile</hi> into his ſu j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction,<note place="margin">Subdues <hi>Galile.</hi>
               </note> except thoſe that dwelt in the Caves: and ſo giving to every one of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers a hundred and fifty <hi>Drachm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and more to his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſm fled them into their winter quarters.</p>
            <p>There came <hi>Silo</hi> to him with his Captains who had win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus,</hi> and who now would maintain them no longer comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding the Inhabitants thereabout to ſpoil the Country of all v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctuals, and to retire to the mountains that the <hi>Romans</hi> might p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſh through famine: But <hi>Herod</hi> committed the charge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f proviſions to his Brother <hi>Phero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and withall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drium</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built.</note> commanded him to rebuild <hi>Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> who in a ſhort time furn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed the ſouldiers with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries, and built again <hi>Alexandrium</hi> that had formerly been diſmantled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ventilius</hi> in <hi>Syri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſent for <hi>Silo</hi> to aſſiſt him againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> but commanded him firſt to aſſiſt <hi>Herod,</hi> and to bring <hi>Herod,</hi> and the reſt of the Auxiliaries of thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40260:9"/> Provinces along with him: But <hi>Herod</hi> ſending <hi>Silo</hi> to him, went himſelf with his Souldiers againſt the Thieves that lived in Caves; and in the mean time made <hi>Ptolomy</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Country, which fell out ill for him; for being ſet upon by thoſe who had formerly diſturbed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, he was ſlain by them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſlain.</note> alter which they retired into Fennes, and inacceſſible places, inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſting with their inrodes, and robberies all the Country: But when <hi>Herod</hi> returned, he made them pay deer for their the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es: for ſome of them he killed, oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs flying to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rcified places he purſued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> beats the Thieves.</note> and having taken them, put them to death, and raſed their ſtrong hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in an hundred T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lents.</p>
            <p>About this time <hi>An h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> commanded <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> to ſend <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> with two Legion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and a thouſand Horſe; but when he came, being corrupted by <hi>Antigonus</hi> with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ney, he would nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s go to him, againſt <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, under a colour of obſerving his actions: But <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſuſpecting him, denied him admittance, and drave him away with ſlings, whereby he found that <hi>Herod</hi> had given him good counſell, and blamed himſelf for not following of it: whereupon he retyred to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> and in his march ki led all the <hi>Jews</hi> that came to hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Machaeras</hi> his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> without diſtinction of friend or foe, being provoked by <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus</hi> his dealing: At which cruelty <hi>Herod</hi> was much grieved, intending to go to <hi>Anth ny,</hi> and ſaying, that he needed other manner of men than thoſe who did him more hurt than his enemies, whereas of himſelf he was able to ſubdue <hi>Antigonus:</hi> But <hi>Machae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as</hi> overtaking him, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed him to ſtay, or if he was reſolve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to go on, yet at leaſt that he would leave with him his Brother <hi>J ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that with their united forces they might make war upon <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus.</hi> Thus after much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty he was reconciled to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chaeras,</hi> and ſo leaving his Brother <hi>J ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with his Army, he commanded him in his abſence that he ſhould not put a l to the hazard of a battail; but himſelf haſted to <hi>Anthony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> goes to <hi>Anthony.</hi>
               </note> whom he found beſieging <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a City near to the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and carried a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g with him ſome Auxiliaries both of Horſe, and Foot. <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ny</hi> entertained him very honourably, and much prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him for his valour.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40260:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph,</hi> unmindfull of his Brothers command, taking with him his own forces, and five <hi>Romane</hi> Cohorts that were given him by <hi>Machaeras,</hi> went towards <hi>Jericho,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to reap the enemies Corn, now that it was ripe, and encamped in the mountains, becauſe the <hi>Romane</hi> Cohorts were raw Souldiers, moſt of them being lately taken up in <hi>Syria:</hi> yet there he was circumvented by the enemy in the middeſt of thoſe faſtneſſes, and having loſt ſix Cohorts, he himſelf valiantly fighting, was ſlain:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> is ſlain.</note> 
               <hi>Antigonus</hi> being in a rage, cauſed the dead body of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to be whipped, though <hi>Pheroras</hi> his Brother, offered fifty Talents to have redeemed it: After this loſs, the <hi>Galilaeans</hi> revolting from their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, drowned thoſe that were of <hi>Herods</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rty in the Lake: In <hi>Idumaea</hi> alſo there were many innovation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anthony</hi> having made peace with his enemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Cains Soſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> to aſſiſt <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> againſt <hi>Antig us</hi> with two Cohorts: When <hi>Herod</hi> came to <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phne,</hi> the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urb of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> he heard of his Brother <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phs</hi> death, which cauſed him to haſten his journey, and coming to Mount <hi>Liba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he took thence with him eight hundred men, and one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſo came to <hi>Pt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mais,</hi> from whence in the night he paſſed with his Army through <hi>Galile:</hi> Here his enemies met him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> whom he overcame in fight and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them into the Caſtle, from whence they had iſſued the day before: Them he aſſaulted, but was compelled to deſiſt by reaſon of the extremity of the weather, and to retreat into ſome neighbouring Villages: but upon the coming of another Cohort from <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ny,</hi> they in the Caſtle were ſo affrighted, that they forſook the ſame by night: <hi>Herod</hi> then haſtned to <hi>Jericho,</hi> purpoſing to revenge his Brothers death: and being come thither, he feaſted his No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, and the feaſt being ended,<note place="margin">A ſpeciall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> and his gueſts diſmiſſed, he retired into his chamber, and preſently the room wherein they had ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, being now empty of company fell down without hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any, which made many to think that ſurely <hi>Herod</hi> was beloved of God who had ſo miraculouſly preſerved him.</p>
            <p>The next day ſix thouſand of the enemies came down from the Mountains to fight with him, and their forlorn-hope
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40260:10"/> with darts and ſtones ſo terrified the <hi>Romans</hi> and ſome of <hi>Herods</hi> Souldiers that they fled, and <hi>Herod</hi> himſelf recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a wound in his ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antigonus,</hi> deſiring to have his ſtrength ſeem greater than it was, ſent one of his Captains, named <hi>Pappus,</hi> with ſome forces into <hi>Samaria,</hi> whileſt himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf went againſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeras.</hi> In the mean time <hi>Herod</hi> took in five Towns, and therein put two thouſand of the Garriſon Souldiers to the ſword, and ſetting the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owns on fire, he went againſt <hi>Pap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> and was ſtrengthened by many that came to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of <hi>Jerico</hi> and <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> yet was the enemy ſo confident that he would j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yn bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le with him, but in fight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> beats his Enemies.</note> 
               <hi>H rod</hi> overcame them, and being inflamed with a deſire to revenge his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death, he purſued th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that fled, ſl w many of them, and fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owed them into a Village, and there ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w many more o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them who retreated into houſes, the reſt fled: After which victory, <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> had preſently gone to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and put an end to the warre, had not the ſhar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſs of the winter hindred him; for now <hi>Antigonus</hi> bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to leave the City, and fly elſwhere for ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> in the evening, when he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſmiſſed his Friends to refreſh themſelves,<note place="margin">A ſpeciall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> a yet hot in his Armour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> went into a chamber, attended with one only ſervant to waſh himſelf, wherein ſome of his enemie armed whom fear had forced thither, were hidden; and whileſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was naked, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, firſt one, and then a ſecond, and a third, ran out armed with naked ſwords in their hands ſo aſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſhed that they were glad to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve themſ lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff ring the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urt to the King. The n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt day <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> amongſt others cut off <hi>Pappus</hi> his head, and ſent it by way of reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge for his Brothers death, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pappus</hi> ſlain.</note> for it was <hi>Pappus</hi> that with his own hand had ſl in <hi>J ſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> in the beginning of the th rd year after he had been declared King at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her d <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſieges</hi> Jeruſalem.</note> comin with an Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> encamped ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the City, and from thence remov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to that p ace where the Wall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were fitteſt to be aſſaulted, he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ched his Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts before the Temple, intending to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt them, as <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpey</hi> had done in times paſt: and h ving
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40260:11"/> encompaſſed the place with three Bulworks, by the help of many workmen he raiſed his batteries; fetching mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials from all places thereabouts, and appointing fit men to overſee the work; and then himſelf went to <hi>Samaria</hi> to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize his Marriage with <hi>Mariamne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marries <hi>Mariamne.</hi>
               </note> the Daughter of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> who was formerly betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to him.</p>
            <p>The Marriage ceremony being over, <hi>Soſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> came with an Army of Horſe and Foot, being ſent by <hi>Anthony</hi> to the aid of <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> alſo took a great party with him from <hi>Samaria</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> ſo that the whole Army being come together, conſiſted of eleven Legions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſix thouſand Horſe, beſides the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Auxiliaries, which were very many, and ſo they pitched on the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the City. Over this great Army were two Generals, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Herod,</hi> who purpoſed to diſplace <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus</hi> as an enemy to the people of <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and to eſtabliſh <hi>Herod</hi> in the Kingdom according to the Decree of the Senate.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> being gathered together out of the whole Country,<note place="margin">The <hi>Jews</hi> fight vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly.</note> and ſhut up within the Walls, made a valiant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, boaſting much of <hi>the Temple of the Lord,</hi> and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Lord would not forſake his people in the time of danger. By ſecret ſallies alſo they burnt up, and ſpoiled all proviſion without the City both for Man and Horſe, whereby the beſiegers began to be pinched: But <hi>Herod</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt their excurſions, by placing ambuſhments in convenient places, and ſending parties to fetch in proviſion from afar off, ſo that in a ſhort time the Army was well furniſhed with all neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of the multitude of workmen the three Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works were ſoon finiſhed, it being Summer time, ſo that no untemperateneſs of weather hindered them: and with his Engins <hi>Herod</hi> often battered the Walls, and left nothing unaſſayed: but the beſieged fought valiantly, and were eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way as active and ſubtile to make void his endeavours; often ſallying forth, and firing their works, both thoſe that were finiſhed, and others that were but begun, and coming to handiſtrokes with the <hi>Romans,</hi> they were nothing infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40260:11"/> to them but only in Martiall skill.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sabbaticall</hi> year now coming,<note place="margin">A Famine in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
               </note> brought a famine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beſieged <hi>Jews,</hi> notwithſtanding which they built a new Wall within that which was beaten down by the battering <hi>Rams,</hi> and ſo countermined the Enemies mines, that many times they came to handiſtrokes under gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und, and making uſe of deſpair inſtead of courage, they held it out unto the laſt, though <hi>Pollio,</hi> the <hi>Phari ee,</hi> and <hi>Samias</hi> his Diſciple adviſed them to receive <hi>Herod</hi> into the City, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld not avoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his being their King by reaſon of their ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They held out the ſiege for five moneths ſpace, though there was ſo great an Army before the City: But at length twenty of <hi>Herods</hi> choiſeſt Souldiers got upon the Wall, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter them the Centurions or <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſius.</hi> So that the firſt Wall was taken on the forti'th day, and the ſecond on the fiftieth, and ſome Galleries about the Temple were burnt down, which <hi>Herod</hi> charged (though falſly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>Antigonus,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bring him into hatred with the people. When the outward part of the Temple was taken, and the lower Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ws</hi> fled into the inward part of the Temple, and the upper City: and fearing leſt they ſhould be hindred from offering their daily Sacrifices unto God, they ſent Ambaſſadors unto <hi>Herod,</hi> to deſire leave that ſuch Beaſts only might be brought in which were to be ſacrificed: This requeſt <hi>Herod</hi> eaſily granted, hoping that by this means they would leave their obſtinacy, and ſubmit to him. But perceiving that this courteſie prevailed not, and that they were ſtill reſolute to continue the Soveraignty in <hi>Antigonus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> taken by <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note> he gave a generall aſſault and won the City on the <hi>Kalends</hi> of <hi>Janu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry,</hi> on the ſecond moneth, <hi>Ciſlu,</hi> being the day on which the <hi>Jews</hi> were wont to celebrate a Faſt in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the holy Rowl that was burnt by <hi>Jehoiakim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City being taken by aſſault, all places were filled with murthers: the <hi>Romans</hi> being incenſed againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> for holding out ſo long;<note place="margin">Cruelty.</note> and the <hi>Herodian Jews</hi> endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to extirpate the contrary faction, ſo that there were continuall ſlaughters in the Porches, and Houſes, yea, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40260:12"/> reverence of the Temple not ſaving the ſuppliants: They ſpared neither age nor ſex, nor ſo much as the little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and though the Conquerou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſought and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them to forbear, yet none would hear, or obey him, but as if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, h y proceeded in their cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antigonus</hi> comi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upper City, fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> his feet, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thing pittying his miſerable condition, inſulted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antigonus</hi> impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> calli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Antigonus,</hi> and withall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> priſon, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs about him.</p>
            <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Strang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, that <hi>Herod</hi> had hired, came ruſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> only, but even into the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuary, ſome he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in by intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, others by t reat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ging his victory worſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> any of thoſe things which were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wind to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to the view of the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> He reſtraine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſo the plun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Cry as much i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in him lay: Intrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> to do the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aski<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, if the <hi>R m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would make him King of a Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erneſs, the City being ſo waſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and murthers: <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uldiers d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſired the plund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry in regar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their hard ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce in the ſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ſaves the City.</note> To which <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eplie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t he woul r com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence every man out of his own Treaſury, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king good his promiſe, he freed the City from urther miſery: F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r he beſtowed gifts liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Souldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably upon the Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nders,<note place="margin">Rewards, the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
               </note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon <hi>Soſius:</hi> wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upon <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> off ring a Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gold unto GOD, withdrew out of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ity, leading <hi>Antig nus</hi> a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, along w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th him to <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> being thus ſetle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he advanced thoſe of his own faction, and duly put to death them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rods</hi> cruelty.</note> Amongſt whom, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo ſlew all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim,</hi> who had accuſed him of a capitall crime, be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re he was King, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mias,</hi> his Diſciple, whom he hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d.</p>
            <p>Then did he gather together all the Regall O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aments, and much ſilver and gold which he ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted from rich me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, all which he gave to <hi>Anthony</hi> and his Souldiers. He put to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40260:12"/> death alſo forty and five of <hi>Antigonus</hi> his chief Noble men, ſetting watches at their doors that none of them might be carried out under pretence of being dead: and what gold or ſilver ſoever was found, was all carried to <hi>Herod,</hi> ſo that there was no end of the peoples miſeries, the covetouſneſs of the needy conquerours conſuming all their eſtates. The fields alſo lay untilled, becauſe it was the <hi>Sabbaticall</hi> year, in which it was unlawfull to ſow the ground.</p>
            <p>Of theſe miſerable times, amongſt others, were ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,<note place="margin">Who were ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tors of it.</note> 
               <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Prieſt, with his Wife <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts of <hi>Davids</hi> ſtock, <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph: Anna</hi> alſo the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of the Tribe of <hi>Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and <hi>Simeon</hi> the Juſt, who received an anſwer from the Holy Ghoſt, that <hi>he ſhould not ſee death, till he had ſeen the Lord Chriſt.</hi> Luk. 2.26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anth ny</hi> being thus poſſeſſed of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> intended to keep him Priſoner to adorn his Triumph; But <hi>Herod</hi> feared that if <hi>Antigonus</hi> was brought to <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Anthony,</hi> he might there contend with him before the Senate for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Conſidering alſo how the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> hated him, and favoured <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus:</hi> he thereupon gave great ſums of money to <hi>Anth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny</hi> to cut off his head,<note place="margin">Anthony <hi>ſlew</hi> Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus.</note> which accordingly he did at <hi>Antioch: Antigo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> being the firſt King that was thus put to death by the <hi>Romans:</hi> and in him ended the Principality of the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> It being from the Captain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Judas M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccabaeus</hi> to the death of <hi>Antig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus</hi> a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred twenty ſix years, and two or three moneths, and by this means <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a ſtranger, got the Kingdom, and was totally freed from his fears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>as</hi> (as we heard before) being carried Priſoner to <hi>Phraates,</hi> the King of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> he intreated him cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly for the Nobility of his deſcent, and after a time, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him from Priſon, he ſuffered him to live in <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> honoured in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </note> where were great ſtore of <hi>Jews,</hi> who honoured him no leſs than as their King and High Prieſt: and not only they of <hi>Babylon,</hi> but all the reſt of the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> did the like, who in old time had been carried captive beyond the River <hi>Euphrates</hi> by the <hi>Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rians,</hi> of whom there were many millions. But <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> hearing that <hi>Herod</hi> was made
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40260:13"/> King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> he began to caſt his hopes that ways, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting favour from <hi>Herod,</hi> whoſe life he had ſaved when he was called in queſtion before the <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi> He conſulted therefore with the <hi>Jews</hi> that came to viſit him, about his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>Judaea,</hi> who by all means diſſwaded him from it, yet could they not prevail with him. Beſides, <hi>Herod</hi> deſired by all means to get the poor old man into his clutches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ſubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lty.</note> and thereupon wrote to him to get leave of <hi>Phraates,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> that he might return, and that they would not envy him the joint ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with his Son in Law, the time being now come wherein he could requite the favours that <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> had ſhewed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in being his nouriſh r, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. He ſent alſo his Ambaſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or to <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> with great Preſents, intre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting him that he would not hinder him from being thankfull to him that had deſerved ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of him. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> being forward of himſelf, diſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed by the <hi>Parthian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and honourably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>niſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for the expences of his j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urney, he came at laſt to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him with all honour, gave him the upper hand in all Aſſemblies, and the more honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able place at all feaſts, calling him <hi>Fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> hereby to delu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him, leſt he ſhould ſuſpect any treach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hananeel</hi> made High-prieſt.</note>
               <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod</hi> providing that none of the Nobility ſhould be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated High-Prieſt, ſent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for a Prieſt of a baſe paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, whom formerly he had been acq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainted with, of the rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Prieſts that had been carried away beyond <hi>Euphrate,</hi> whoſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me was <hi>Ananclius,</hi> or <hi>Hananeel,</hi> and to him he gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ieſthoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> takes it ill.</note>This <hi>Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> the Daughter of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> the Wife of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> the Son of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Mother in Law of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> took in ill part; for that <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> her Son, and Brother of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neglected, and another from a ſtrange place ſhould be made High-Prieſt: whereupon ſhe wrote to <hi>Cleopatra</hi> Queen of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Anthoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> darling, that ſhe would procure the High-Prieſthood of <hi>Anth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for her Son. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> neglected her requeſt; but ſhortly after, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> a friend of <hi>Anth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> coming into <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſwaded her to ſend the Pictures of her Son <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bulus,</hi> and of her
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40260:13"/> Daughter <hi>Mariamne</hi> to <hi>Anthony,</hi> who then would deny her nothing: This ſhe aſſented to, and ſent them by <hi>Dellius,</hi> who told <hi>Anthony</hi> that they ſeemed rather to be of a Divine than of a humane race.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anthony</hi> was much inflamed herewith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anthony</hi> ſends for <hi>Ariſtobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
               </note> yet thought it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent to ſend for a Lady that was married to <hi>Herod,</hi> ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo the jealouſie of <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> whereupon he wrote to <hi>Alexandra</hi> to ſend her Son to him under ſome honeſt pretence: But theſe things coming to the ears of <hi>Herod,</hi> he thought it not ſafe that <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tobulus,</hi> now in the flower of his age, being but ſixteen, ſhould be ſent to <hi>Anthony,</hi> the moſt potent man amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and very much given to his luſts. Wherefore he wrote back, that if the youth did but ſtep out of the Kingdom, all the Country would be up in Arms, the <hi>Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hoping for ſome innovations under a new King, and by this means he ſatisfied <hi>Anthony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> being continually moleſted with the intreaties of his Wife <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mne,</hi> that he would give the High-Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to her Brother <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tobulus,</hi> it being his right, he called a Councel of his frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, to whom he inveighed againſt his Mother in Law <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>xandra,</hi> as if ſhe had privately wrought treaſon againſt his Kingdom, and had indeavoured by <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi>'s means to tranſlate it to young <hi>Ariſtobulus;</hi> yet, leſt he ſhould ſeem to neglect both his piety to her, and the reſt of that kindred, he told them he would now reſtore the Prieſthood to her Son,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> made High-Prieſt.</note> which hitherto <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anelus</hi> had ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y reaſon of the young mans tender years: <hi>Alexan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra</hi> being herewith overjoyed, and withall grieved th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſuſpected, tell a weeping, clearing her ſelf of thoſe accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and gave him many thank for her Sons honour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing that hereafter ſhe would be moſt obedient unto him And thus <hi>Herod,</hi> in the life-time of <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> gave the High-Prieſthood to <hi>Ari <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bulus,</hi> being then but ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>venteen years old.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Herod</hi> fearing leſt his Mother in Law <hi>Alexandra</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexandra</hi> confined.</note> ſhould ſeek occaſion to raiſe new troubles, confined her to the Palace, and commanded her to do nothing by her own authority: yea, he ſet ſo ſtrict a guard over her, that nothing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40260:14"/> was concealed from him of all that ſhe did, to the very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of her Table. This ſhe took very heavily, and wrote to <hi>Cleopatra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">She com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains to <hi>Cleopatra.</hi>
               </note> complaining of her hard condition, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her to yield her aſſiſtance: <hi>Cleopatra</hi> adviſed her with her Son to fly to her into <hi>Egypt,</hi> which ſhe liked, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore provided two Coffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, one for her ſelf, the other for her Son, commanding her ſervants that were privy to the plot, to carry them out by night, and to convey them to a Ship that was ready prepared to carry them into <hi>Egypt.</hi> This buſineſs <hi>Aeſopus,</hi> one of her ſervants, blabbed to <hi>Sabbation,</hi> a friend of <hi>Alexanders,</hi> ſuppoſing that he had known all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: which as ſoon as <hi>Sabbati n</hi> knew, though hitherto he was an enemy of <hi>Herods,</hi> as being ſuſpected to have been in the plot of poiſoning his Father <hi>Antipa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he took this occaſion of being reconciled to the King, by diſcovering the matter.<note place="margin">She is ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> being thus informed of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the matter till it was in execution, and then ſurpriſed her in her flight, and brought her back: Yet did he pardon her fault, not indeed daring to puniſh her, leſt thereby he ſhould diſcontent <hi>Cle patra,</hi> that was willing to take any occaſion againſt him: wherefore under a colour of a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous ſpirit, he made ſhew as if he pardoned her out of meer clemency.</p>
            <p>The Feaſt of <hi>Tabernacles</hi> being now come, the new High-Prieſt <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> being juſt paſt ſeventeen years old, was to offer Sacrifice according to the Law, and being clad in his Pontificall attire, he came to the Altar, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Ceremony with all decency, whoſe excellent beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> highly ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured.</note> being higher than was uſuall for his age, and carrying in his countenance the honour of his Linage, drew the eyes, and love of all the multitude upon him, every one calling to mind the worthy, and memorable actions of his Grandfather <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tobulus,</hi> and therefore, as overcome with affections towards him, they were ſo overjoyed that they could not contain themſelves, but openly prayed for him, and wiſhed him all joy, and that more freely than was meet in thoſe jealous times under ſuch a King, proclaiming openly both the memory, and thanks that they owed to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40260:14"/> the Famely for all the benefits they had received from it.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Feaſt was ended, <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at a Banquet by his Mother <hi>Alexandra: Herod</hi> alſo pretended favour to him, and enticed him into a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent place to ſport with him after the manner of young men, and when they were hot, and weary, and left their ſport, they walked out to the Fiſh Ponds, which were near the Court to take the freſh air, where alſo they beheld ſome of the ſervants that were ſwimming: At laſt by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Herod, Arriobulus</hi> undreſt himſelf and went in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: Then they, who were ſuborned by <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> as it were in ſport and jeſt, ducked him as he was ſwiming, holding him under water,<note place="margin">He is drowned.</note> and never left off till they had drowned him. This was the end of <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> in the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of his age, and in the firſt year of his High-Prieſthood, which immediatly returned to <hi>Ananelus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The report of theſe things coming to the Women, they were all on an uprore, and did nothing but weep, and howl over the body of the young man: Yea ſorrow overſpread the whole City, every one bewailing the calamity as if it had been h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s own: But <hi>Herod</hi> endeavoured by all means to make the people beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve as if it had faln out by chance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his privity, not only feigning ſorrow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ſubtilty.</note> but tears and grief alſo: and that he might the more comfort the Women, he buried the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in a moſt magnificent manner, being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall to prodigality in adorning his Monument, and in perfumes, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>recious things.</p>
            <p>But his Mother <hi>Alexan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra,</hi> knowing the treaſon, though ſhe was oft ready to lay violent han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s u on her ſelf, yet repreſſed her paſſion, ſeeming not to be ſuſpicious, till an opportunity of revenge might offer it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And ſhortly after ſhe wrote to <hi>Cleopatra</hi> of the treachery of <hi>Herod,</hi> and of the lamentable death of her Son.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexandra</hi> complains to <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cleopatra</hi> pittying her misfortune, to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k a particular care of thi buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if it had been her own, and never reſted from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading <hi>Antho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to revenge the you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g mans death: telling him that it was an unpardonable crime, that he who by his help, enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed a Kingdom that was anothers right,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40260:15"/> ſhould rage ſo inſolently againſt the famely of the lawfull Kings. <hi>Anthony</hi> being prevailed with hereby, when he came to <hi>Laodicea</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> ſent for <hi>Herod</hi> to come before him to anſwer what ſhould be objected againſt him about the Death of <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bulus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Anth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Herod,</hi> during t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> time of his abſence committed the care of his King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>p,</hi> privately commanding him, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould do him any miſchief, he ſhould preſently put his W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe <hi>Mariamne</hi> to death, pretending that he ſo lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her, that he ſhould eſteem it a great wrong if any but himſelf ſhould enjoy her beauty, yea though it was after his Death.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Herod</hi> came to <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he ſo appeaſed him with rich preſents that he brought on purpoſe with him from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">But cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his bribes.</note> and by his frequent conferences with him, that afterwards <hi>Cleopatr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s inſtigations prevailed little: For <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> ſaid, that it was not fit that a King ſhould be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for his actions, otherwiſe he would ceaſe to be a King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For having once given him the honour, the free exerciſe of his Kingly power was to be admitted unto him. He told <hi>Cleopatra</hi> alſo, that it was not fit for her too much to meddle with other mens matters.</p>
            <p>During <hi>Herods</hi> abſence, <hi>Joſeph</hi> governing the Kingdom, he had occaſion many times to converſe with <hi>Mariamne,</hi> partly upon buſineſs, and partly to do her honour, and in their diſcourſes there was often mention made how much <hi>Herod</hi> loved her, which diſcourſe was laughed at by the Ladies, eſpecially by <hi>Alexandra:</hi> But he was carried on with ſuch a deſire of proving the Kings love to them, that he told them what private command the King had given him, ſuppoſing this was an infallible argument of his love, becauſe he could neither endure to live without her, nor in death to be diſjoyned from her: but the Ladies were not of his mind, rather abhorring the Tyranny of <hi>Herod,</hi> who, though he were dead, yet would he ſeek their lives.</p>
            <p>Preſently after a rumour was ſpread about the City, that <hi>Anthony</hi> had put <hi>Herod</hi> to death, which much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all the Court, eſpecially the Ladies: whereupon <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40260:15"/> perſwaded <hi>Joſeph;</hi> that, taking them along with him, he ſhould fly to the <hi>Romane</hi> Legions that lay before the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under the command of the Tribune <hi>Julius,</hi> ſo that if any trouble aroſe in the City, they might be ſecured by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans:</hi> adding, that ſhe hoped if <hi>Mariamne</hi> came but once to the ſight of <hi>Anthony,</hi> ſhe might obtain any thing of him, yea, even the Kingdom, with whatſoever belonged to the Royall Famely.</p>
            <p>Whileſt theſe things were under debate, there came Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from <hi>Herod,</hi> which daſhed all, ſignifying how <hi>Anthony</hi> had honoured him both in the publick <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> and in inviting him to his Feaſts, and that, during the accuſations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> ſo that he feared her not for the time to come, but hoped ſhortly to return to them, <hi>Anthony</hi> having given <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ria</hi> unto <hi>Cleopatra</hi> inſtead of <hi>Judea,</hi> upon condition that ſhe ſhould not hereafter demand <hi>Judea,</hi> nor trouble him any further about that buſineſs.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as theſe Letters were received, the ſpeech about flying to the <hi>Romans</hi> vaniſhed, but yet their debate about it was not hid; For as ſoon as <hi>Herod</hi> had brought <hi>Anthony</hi> part of his way againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> he returned into <hi>Judea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods,</hi> return.</note> and immediatly his Siſter <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lome,</hi> and his Mother <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> told him what <hi>Alexandra</hi>'s counſel was; neither was ſhe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with contented, but ſhe accuſed her Husband <hi>Joſeph,</hi> as if he had been too familiar with <hi>Mariamne:</hi> and this ſhe did out of an old grudge, becauſe the Queen (a woman of an high ſpirit) in their womanly brabbles, had upbraided her with her obſcure birth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mariamne</hi> by her Oath aſſured <hi>Herod</hi> of her chaſtity, who told her again how much he loved her; but ſhe replied, that it was not the part of a lover, to command that if he died, ſhe ſhould be put to death alſo. <hi>Herod</hi> judging that this ſecret could never be known, except ſhe had committed adultery with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> had much ado to refrain from killing her immediatly: but love overcoming his paſſion, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained; yet did he command <hi>Joſeph</hi> to be put to death<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> put to death.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuffering him to plead for himſelf, <hi>Alexandra</hi> alſo he caſt into priſon, as the cauſe of all theſe evils.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40260:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleopatra</hi> having brought <hi>Anthony</hi> part of his way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Parthia,</hi> returned towards <hi>Egypt,</hi> and by the way, was entertained by <hi>Herod,</hi> who aſſured unto her that part of <hi>Arabia</hi> which was granted unto her by <hi>Anthony,</hi> to which he added the reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues of <hi>Jericho,</hi> where are great ſtore of the beſt Date Trees and where Balſom grows,<note place="margin">Gardens of Balſom.</note> which being a precious Oyntment only grows there, in two Gardens, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h which are the King, the one of twenty Acres, the other of leſs.</p>
            <p>By this means <hi>Herod</hi> grew into great familiarity with <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> who ſought to aſſure him to her luſt, either through her great intemperance, or becauſe ſhe ſought by this means to betray him; but though ſhe pretended love to him, yet <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> refuſed, and held a conſultation with his friends about killing her, who diſſwaded him from it, and therefore having appeaſed her by great preſents, and all manner of obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiouſneſs, he accompanied her as far as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſium:</hi> yet ſearing both her, and the people of the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he reſerved the Caſtle as a refuge for himſelf, laying in as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arms there as were ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient for ten thouſand men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> paved duly to <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>patra</hi> the Tributes of <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aea</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> which <hi>Anthony</hi> had given to her, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thinking it ſafe to give her any occaſion of diſguſt againſt him,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being now free from troubles, and having taken <hi>Hyrc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a Town which hitherto a Siſter of <hi>Antigonus</hi> had kept, the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> War brake forth between <hi>Auguſtus Caeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whereupon <hi>Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> made great preparation for the aſſiſting of <hi>Anth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to aſſiſt <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony.</hi>
               </note> but he freed him from the trouble, telling him that he needed them not, and ſo diſmiſhing him, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> returned home with a well-fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Army, wherewith he invaded <hi>Arabia,</hi> going as far as <hi>Dioſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis,</hi> at which place the <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bians</hi> met him, and after a fierce confl ct, the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ws</hi> gat the victory.</p>
            <p>After this <hi>Herod</hi> made many inrodes into <hi>Arabia</hi> in the ſeventh year of his raign after the death of <hi>Antigorus,</hi> at which time the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> War being begun,<note place="margin">A great Earrh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</note> 
               <hi>Judea</hi> was ſhaken with ſuch an Earthquake as never was the like before, in which ten thouſand men were overwhelmed by the ruins
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40260:16"/> of the houſes, yet the Souldiers received no dammage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lay in the open fields. This being much aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated by report, ſo emboldned the <hi>Arabians,</hi> that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y laid hold on the Ambaſſadours of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who, in this their affliction came to demand peace, and ſlew them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently prepared for war with all earneſtneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> hearing hereof, encouraged his men, offered Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice according to the cuſtom, and ſo in all haſt, marched with his Army over <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdan,</hi> and having incamped at <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia,</hi> there the fight began about the taking of a Caſtle that lay between him, and the <hi>Arabians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> overcoms the <hi>Arabians.</hi>
               </note> in which the <hi>Jews</hi> got the better, and after continuall skirmiſhes, forced the <hi>Arabians</hi> to flight, who in their haſt treading one upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, they loſt in all five thouſand men: the reſt were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged in their Camp, and extreamly wanting water, they ſent Ambaſſadours to <hi>Herod,</hi> who would not admit of them, and was more eager upon them for offering but fifty Talents for their freedom: They being parched with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall thirſt, came out of their Camp by great companies, offering themſelves to the <hi>Jews,</hi> by which means they took five thouſand of them in five days: and at laſt the reſt in the Camp came out to fight; but deſpairing of any good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, there fell of them in the firſt conflict about ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more. By this overthrow the courage of the <hi>Arabians</hi> was tamed, and <hi>Herod</hi> was declared Governour of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo returned home with great Glory.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Actian</hi> war being finiſhed, wherein <hi>Caeſar</hi> finally overthrew <hi>Anthony, Alexandra</hi> hoped that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould be ſeverely puniſhed by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for aſſiſting <hi>Anthony</hi> againſt him, whereupon ſhe ſollicited her Father <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> not any longer to ſuffer the affliction of their Family,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra's</hi> reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs.</note> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reſerve himſelf for better times: For which end ſhe adviſed him to ſeek for protection and entertainment of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lchus,</hi> the King of <hi>Arabia.</hi> Theſe ſollicitations her Father at firſt repulſed, but at laſt being overcome by her woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh importunity, he ſent Letters to <hi>Malchus</hi> by one <hi>Doſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> a friend of his, deſiring him to ſend ſome Horſmen to convey him to the Lake <hi>Asphaltitis,</hi> which is diſtant from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40260:17"/> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> about three hundred furlongs. This <hi>Doſicheus</hi> was kinſman to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom <hi>Herod</hi> had put to death, yet, to curry favour with the King, he ſhewed him the Letters: <hi>Herod</hi> thanked him, and withall deſired one curteſie more, that he would ſeal up the Letters, and give them to <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> and bring his anſwer to him. This he did, and the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſent back word, that he was ready to entertain <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> and his Famely, and all the <hi>Jews</hi> that were of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that he would ſend a band of Souldiers to conduct them in ſafety, who ſhould be obedient to <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anus</hi> in all things. <hi>Herod</hi> having received this anſwer, called <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> and asked him if he had any confederacy with <hi>Malchus?</hi> who denying it, he produced the Letters in the Councel of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and commanded him to be put to death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> goes to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having thus diſpatched <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> reſolved to poſt unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and expecting no good from him, becauſe of his great friendſhip to <hi>Anthony,</hi> he was very jealous of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandra,</hi> leſt, taking this oportunity, ſhe ſhould ſtir up the people to rebell, and ſo fill the Kingdom with domeſticall ſeditions. Wherefore committing the care of his Kingdom to his Brother <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roras,</hi> he left his Mother <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Salome,</hi> and all his kindred in the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Maſſada:</hi> And commanded his Brother, that if any thing befell him otherwiſe than well, he ſhould retain the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom in his own hands: and becauſe his Wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> by reaſon of ſome differences, could not live with his Mother, he placed her with her Mother <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xandri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> committing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he cuſtody of them to his Treaſurer <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and to <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> an <hi>Ituria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> under a colour of doing them honour, but yet he gave them this command, that it they ſhould certainly know that any ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hap befell him,<note place="margin">His cruel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</note> they ſhould preſently put both the Ladies to death, and to the uttermoſt of their power, keep the Kingdom for his Children, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Brother <hi>Pheroras.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having thus ſetled his affairs at home, poſted to <hi>Rhodes</hi> to meet with <hi>Caeſar</hi> there, whither when he was come, laying only his Crown aſide, but retaining other his Princely Ornaments, he was admitted into <hi>Caeſars</hi> preſence,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40260:17"/> where, with great conſtancy, and magnanimity of ſpirit, he freely confeſſed the love he bore to <hi>Anthony,</hi> as alſo the ſupplies he had ſent him of Corn, and Money: adding moreover that he was ready with the ſame Faith to keep friendſhip with <hi>Caeſar.</hi> This <hi>Caeſar</hi> exhorted him to,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours him.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring his Crown to him, exceedingly honoured him. Thus beyond all expectation, is <hi>Herod</hi> again confirmed in his Kingdom, both by the free gift of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and alſo by a Decree of the Senate, which <hi>Caeſar</hi> procured for him: and <hi>Herod</hi> gave great Preſents both to <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf, and to all his friends about him, even above his ability, to ſhew the greatneſs of his mind</p>
            <p>During his abſence, his Wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His wife and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are full of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents.</note> and his Mother <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndra,</hi> took it very ill that they were ſhut up in that Caſtle as in a Priſon, ſo that they could neither enjoy their own, nor make uſe of other mens goods: eſpecially when by their femenine flatteries they had fiſhed out of <hi>Sohemus,</hi> what <hi>Herod</hi> had commanded concerning them: She then began to wiſh that he might never return home, ſuppoſing that ſhe ſhould live a moſt intollerable life with him: all which ſhe afterwards diſſembled not, but openly confeſſed what it was that did afflict her. For <hi>Herod</hi> returning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all expectation, and relating to <hi>Mariamne</hi> what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes he had, ſhe ſeemed not to regard them, and at all the caraſſes that he made her, ſhe would ſigh, ſo that <hi>Herod</hi> plainly perceived the hatred of his Wife againſt him, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that himſelf was wavering between love, and hatred towards her.</p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Caeſar</hi> paſſing through <hi>Syria</hi> towards <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> bounty to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and his Army.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> intertained him with all Royall magnificence at <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olemais,</hi> and ſhewed all hoſpitality towards his Army, giving them plenty of all ſorts of victuals, by which means he was counted one of <hi>Caeſars</hi> chiefeſt friends, and uſed to ride about with him when he muſtred hi Army. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him alſo and his Frinds with a hundred and fifty Men, all clad in moſt ſumptuous, and rich apparell, yea, he ſuff red them to want nothing in their march to <hi>Peluſium,</hi> through barren places, and ſuch as wanted water, yet did he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40260:18"/> provide plentifully for them, with which the Souldiers were much delighted. He alſo preſented <hi>Caeſar</hi> with eight hundred Talents: yea, he gave ſuch ſatisfaction to all, that they confeſſed that it was greater than the Kingdom could afford.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> is jealous of his wife.</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> wavering between love and hatred towards his Wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> was continually incenſed againſt her by the falſe accuſations of his Siſter <hi>Salome,</hi> and his Mother <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pros,</hi> who laboured to kindle his hatred and jealouſie againſt her: whereupon, probably he had proceeded rigorouſly with her, but that news came ſeaſonably that <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> were both dead,<note place="margin">He meets <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </note> and that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had won <hi>Egypt,</hi> and was coming back, whom in all haſt he went to meet, and ſo left his Famely as it was. At his departure he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended <hi>Sohemus</hi> to <hi>Mariamne,</hi> profeſſing that he owed him much reſpect for the care he had had of her: and gave to him alſo the Government of a part of <hi>Judea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> meeting with <hi>Caeſar</hi> before he was come out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in confidence of his Friendſhip, ſpake freely to him, and was highly honoured by him: For he beſtowed upon him the four hundred <hi>Galatians,</hi> who were formerly of <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> Guard, to be his Guard, and reſtored to him that part of his Country which <hi>Cleopatra</hi> had ſeized upon, and added to his Kingdom <hi>Gadara,</hi> and <hi>Hippon,</hi> and <hi>Samaria;</hi> and by the Sea-ſide, <hi>Gaza,</hi> and <hi>Anthedon,</hi> and <hi>Joppa,</hi> and the Tower of <hi>Straton,</hi> which added much ſplendour to his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Caeſars</hi> return through <hi>Syria, Herod</hi> conducted him as far as <hi>Antioch.</hi> At his return, for the ſpace of a whole year, ſuſpicions increaſed daily between him and his Wife <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ſuſpicions of his wife are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</note> ſhe neglecting his caraſſes, and oft upbraiding him either with the death of her Grandfather <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> or her Father <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> ſo that <hi>Herod</hi> could ſcarce refrain from ſtriking her, and <hi>Salome</hi> by the noiſe, perceiving that <hi>Herod</hi> was much moved, ſhe ſent in the Butler, whom long before ſhe had ſuborned for that end, who told <hi>Herod</hi> that he was ſollicited by <hi>Mariamne</hi> to deliver him a love potion, which he had by him, but what it was he knew not. <hi>Herod</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40260:18"/> examined the moſt faithfull ſervant of <hi>Mariamne</hi> by torture, being aſſured that ſhe would attempt nothing without his privily, who not enduring the torments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that ſhe was offended for ſomething that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohemus</hi> had declared unto her, which when the King heard, he cryed out, that <hi>Sohemus,</hi> who had ever been moſt faithfull both to him, and the Kingdom, would never have ſpoken of theſe things, had there not been ſome more ſecret famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity between them than was fitting; and thereupon he commanded <hi>Sohemus</hi> to be apprehended and put to death; and having called his Friends to Counſel, he accuſed his Wife for practiſing to poiſon him, which he ſo aggravated, that all that were preſent perceived that he had a mind that ſhe ſhould be condemned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mariamne</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death.</note> which was accordingly done by the generall conſent of them all: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d whereas they thought that the ex cution ſhould not be over ſpeedy, but rather that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be ſecured i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Caſtles, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome</hi> excee ingly urged the King that ſhe ſhould preſently be put to death, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear leſt there ſhould be ſome commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the people ſhe being alive and in Priſon: and thus was <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mne</hi> brought to h r death.</p>
            <p>When her Mother <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xandra</hi> ſaw her going to execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conſidered that ſhe muſt look for the ſame at <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, that ſhe might not ſeem to be guilty of the ſome crime, ſhe began to up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raid her daughter as being wicked, and ungratefull towards her Husband, ſaying,<note place="margin">Her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocr ſie.</note> 
               <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſhe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved death who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo hamous an act.</hi> Whilſt ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited theſe things, and made as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pulled her Daughter by the hair, they that were preſent co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her hypocriſie;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mariamnes</hi> Death.</note> but ſhe that was led to death returned her no anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, but refelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accuſation, with a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute countenance, and mind, and underwent her death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear.</p>
            <p>She being dead, <hi>Herod</hi> began to be more inflamed with love towards her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive grief for her.</note> often calling upon her Name and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her death beyond decency; and although he ſought to div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt his grief by pleaſures, feaſtings and drinking, yet all availed nothing. Whereupon he caſt off the care of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40260:19"/> Kingdom, and ſo far gave up himſelf to ſorrow, that he would bid his ſervants call <hi>Mariamne,</hi> as though ſhe were y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> living.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>As <hi>Herod</hi> was thus tormenting himſelf, there came a great Plague, which ſwept away a great part both of the Nobility, and Commons, every one judging that this Plague was ſent by God for the unjuſt death of the Queen. The Kings diſcontents being increaſed hereby, he at laſt hid himſelf in a ſolitary Wilderneſs under a pretence of hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; where ſtill afflicting himſelf, he fell into a great ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly and ſickneſſe.</note> which was accompanied with an inflammation and great pain in his neck, ſo that he began to rave; neither could any applications eaſe him, but rather made the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe more painfull, ſo that thoſe about him began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of his life: and his Phyſicians, partly becauſe of the ſtubborneſs of the diſeaſe, and partly becauſe in ſo great danger there was not any free election of diet, they gave him leave to eat whatſoever he would.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Death.</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> lying thus ſick in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Alexandra</hi> being at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhe endeavoured to get the two Caſtles of the City into her hands, the one adjoyning to the Temple, the other ſituate in the City: For which end ſhe ſollicited the Governours of them to deliver them up unto her, and to the Children of her and <hi>Mariamne,</hi> leſt that <hi>Herod</hi> being dead, they ſhould be ſeized upon by others: But they who had ever been faithfull to <hi>Herod,</hi> were now much more diligent in their Office, both out of an hatred of <hi>Alexandra,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought it a great offence to deſpair of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of their Prince. Hereupon they preſently ſent meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to <hi>Herod,</hi> to acquaint him with <hi>Alexandra's</hi> attempt, who thereupon commanded her to be ſlain. At length o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercoming his diſeaſe, he recovered his ſtrength both of body and mind, but grew ſo cruell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> grows cruel. <hi>Salome</hi> leaves her husband and comes to <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note> that upon the leaſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he was ready to put any one to Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salome, Herods</hi> Siſter, having been married to <hi>Coſſaborus</hi> an <hi>Idumean,</hi> a difference now ariſing betwixt them, ſhe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſent him a Bill of Divorce, and came away to her Brother <hi>Herod,</hi> telling him that ſhe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40260:19"/> preferred his love before her tye to her Husband: the reaſon which ſhe pretended was, that <hi>Coſſaborus</hi> had practiſed ſome innovations with <hi>Lyſimachus, Antipater,</hi> and <hi>Doſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> confirming it from this, becauſe he had privily kept in his Country the Children of <hi>Bebas,</hi> now for the ſpace of twelve years from <hi>Herods</hi> taking of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty.</note> As ſoon as <hi>Herod</hi> heard this, he ſent ſome to their hiding places, and killed them, with many others, to the intent that none ſhould remain of the kindred of <hi>Hyrcanus:</hi> He alſo took out of the way all ſuch as excelled in any dignity, that he might do whatſoever ſeemed him good, there being none to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> by theſe practiſes growing more ſecure,<note place="margin">He inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Games to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </note> he began to degenerate more and more from his Country faſhions, violating them by forreign inventions. For firſt he inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted wreſtlings every fifth year in the honour of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for the exhibiting of which, he began to build a Theatre in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and an <hi>Amphitheatre</hi> in the plaine, both of them very ſumptuous for the workmanſhip, but clean contrary to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> cuſtomes: Yea he would have thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſolemnity to be inrolled, and to be proclaimed in the neighbouring Countries, and to remoter Nations, and by propounding great rewards, he invited, not only thoſe that were skilfull wreſtlers, but alſo excellent Muſitians, and ſuch as play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſeverall inſtrum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts Yet that which above all troubled the <hi>Jews,</hi> were the Trophees, which being covered with Armour, they thought to be Images, forbidden by their Law; but <hi>Herod</hi> to ſatisfie them commanded the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to be taken off, and ſhewed them that they were meer ſtocks of wood, whereupon all their anger was turned into laughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having many wayes provoked the <hi>Jews,</hi> ten Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> made a Conſpiracy againſt him,<note place="margin">A conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi>
               </note> amongſt whom one was blind, who made one not becauſe he could do any thing, but to ſhew how ready he was to ſuffer with thoſe that defended their Countrie rights: <hi>Herod</hi> had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſecret ſpies to diſcover ſuch plots, one of which had fiſhed this matter out, and acquainted <hi>Herod</hi> with it, who
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40260:20"/> cauſed them to be apprehended,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators are put to Death.</note> and when they were brought before him, with undaunted countenances they drew out their weapons from under their garments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, that, not out of any private reſpect, but in the behalf of the publick wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they had undertaken this conſpiracy. Then were they led way, and put to death with all manner of tortures. Not long after, their accuſer being hated of all men was ſlai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by ſome, and being cut in pieces, was thrown to the Dogs. Yet were the authors hereof concealed, till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long, and weariſome inquiſitions, it was by torture wrung out from ſome ſilly women who were privie to it When <hi>Herod</hi> had thus found out the authors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods.</hi> cruelty. He forti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> and built a Temple there.</note> he puniſhed them with death, and their whole Famelies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> the better to ſecure himſelf from the ſeditions of the tumultuous people, in the thirt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nth year of his raign, began to fortifie <hi>Samaria,</hi> which was a day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> journey from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and called it <hi>Sebaſte</hi> (or <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi>) The circuit of it was twenty furlongs, in the middeſt whereof he built a Temple of a furlong and an half, which he wonderfully adorned, and ſo ordered, that many of the Souldiers, and of the neighbouring Nations came and dwelt there.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He built ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verall Caſtles.</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> alſo built another Cidadel to be as a bridle to the whole Nation, namely the Tower of <hi>Straton:</hi> Alſo in the great plain he built a Caſtle and choſe of his Horſmen by lot, to keep it. Another he built in <hi>Galile,</hi> and one in <hi>Peraea:</hi> which Caſtles being ſo conveniently diſpoſed in ſeverall parts of the Country, took away from the people all opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of rebellion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plague, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note>About this time very grievous calamities befel the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Firſt there was a long drought, after which followed a Famine: After the Famine, by reaſon of their ill diet, there came divers ſickneſſes, and the Plague; and <hi>Herod,</hi> having not wherewithall to ſupply the publick wants, was forced to melt the gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that was in his Pallace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> care to provide for the people.</note> not ſparing any thing for the curioſity of the workmanſhip: no not ſo much as the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels which were for his own daily uſe. Theſe being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into mony, he ſent to buy proviſions into <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40260:20"/> where <hi>Petronius</hi> was Governour under <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who though he was peſtered with multitudes that repaired to him upon the like neceſſity, yet being <hi>Herods</hi> friend, he gave his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants leave to export Corn, and was aſſiſting to them, both in the buying, and carriage of it.</p>
            <p>When the Corn was brought to <hi>Herod,</hi> he was very carefull to ſee it divided, firſt to ſuch as had moſt need, and then becauſe there were many who by reaſon of old age, or ſome other weakneſſe, were unable to dreſſe it themſelves, he appointed them certain Bakers to provide their food for them: By this means he procured the good will of the people, and the praiſe of a prudent and provident Prince.</p>
            <p>He provided alſo for his ſubjects againſt the ſharpneſſe of the winter, taking care that none ſhould want clothing, their Cattel being dead, and wool, and other materials failing. And when he had made proviſion for his own People,<note place="margin">His boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſtrangers.</note> he took care alſo for the neighbouring Cities of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> to whom he allowed feed for ſowing of their ground: and the Caſtles, and Cities; and thoſe of the Common people, who had great Famelies, coming to him for ſuccour, he found a remedy for them alſo: Inſomuch that he gave to thoſe that were not his Subjects ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Cores of Corn, each Core containing ten <hi>Athenian</hi> buſhels.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Corn was ripe for harveſt, <hi>Herod</hi> diſmiſſed fifty thouſand Men, whom he had fed in the time of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine into their own Countries: by which dilligence he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored the almoſt ruined eſtate of his own Subjects, and did not a little relieve his neighbours, who groaned under the ſame calamities.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time alſo he ſent aid to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to wit,<note place="margin">He ſends aid to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>
               </note> five hundred choſen M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of his own Guard whom <hi>Aelius Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> led into the <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bian</hi> Wars, where they did moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> alſo built himſelf a Pallace in <hi>Sidon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He built himſelf a Pallace.</note> in which he built two very large and ſtately Houſes, with which the Temple it ſelf could in no wiſe compare, and called one of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40260:21"/> them by the name of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the other by the name of <hi>Agrippa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He makes a new High Prieſt: and marries <hi>Mariamne.</hi> He built another Pallace</note>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having removed from the Prieſthood <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Phales,</hi> made <hi>Simon</hi> (a Prieſt of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Son of <hi>Boethus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi>) Prieſt in his room, and took alſo his Daughter <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rimne</hi> to Wife, that was the moſt beautifull Virgin of that age.</p>
            <p>The marriage ſolemnities being over, he began to build another new Pallace, unto which he adjoyned a Town, which he called <hi>Herodion,</hi> in a place diſtant from <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> about ſixty furlongs towards <hi>Arabia,</hi> in the place where he had overcome the <hi>Jew,</hi> when he was thruſt out by the Arms of <hi>Antigonus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and a ſtately Haven.</note>He buil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and having finiſhed that, he beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to build another moſt magnificent City in a place by the Sea-ſide, where <hi>Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> ſtood, which he called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and added to it an Haven of admirable work, equall in bigneſs to the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>raetus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in twelve years ſpace, ſparing neither ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r nor coſt about them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He ſent his ſons to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </note>Then did he ſend hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xander,</hi> and <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> (whom he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>Aſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi>) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to be there educ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for whom Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs were prepared at the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, Herods</hi> great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Caeſar</hi> intertained the young men very cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eouſly, and gave <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> power to make which of his ſons h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed the heir of his Kingdom:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged his Kingdom.</note> he added alſo to his Government <hi>Trach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Herod</hi> had received <hi>Trach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> he took guides, and went to the Den o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Thieve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">He repreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the thieves.</note> reſtraining their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, whereby the peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in quiet: But <hi>Zenodorus,</hi> the former Governour, being move<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtly thorough envy, and partly with the loſſe of his Government, went to <hi>R me</hi> to accuſe <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> but could effect nothing.</p>
            <p>About this time <hi>Herod</hi> went to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to ſalute his chiefeſt friend <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and ſo returned into <hi>Judaea:</hi> and preſently after ſome Citizens of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ra</hi> went to <hi>Agrippa</hi> to accuſe <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He went to <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa.</hi>
               </note> whom he vouchſafed not ſo much as to hear, but ſent them bound to <hi>Herod:</hi> Yet did he ſpare them:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40260:21"/> for though he was inexorable towards his own people, yet did he willingly contemn, and forgive injuries received from ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zenodorus</hi> had ſolemnly ſworn to the <hi>Gadareus,</hi> that he would do his utmoſt with <hi>Caeſar</hi> to get them freed from the juriſdiction of <hi>Herod,</hi> and to be annexed to the Province of <hi>Caeſar:</hi> Many of themſelves alſo exclaimed againſt <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </note> calling him cruell Tyrant, complaining to <hi>Caeſar</hi> of his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and rapines, and for raſing, and robbing their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Yet was <hi>Herod</hi> nothing herewith terrified, being ready to anſwer for himſelf: But <hi>Caeſar</hi> uſed him courteouſly, and was nothing alienated from him for all theſe tumultuous complaints: The <hi>Gadareus</hi> therefore perceiving the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Friends towards <hi>Herod,</hi> deſpairing of good ſucceſs, and fearing to be delivered into <hi>Herods</hi> hands, ſome of them cut their own throats, others fearing tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments brake their own necks, or drowned themſelves in the River, and thus, ſeeming to forejudg themſelves, <hi>Caeſar</hi> abſolved <hi>Herod</hi> from all their accuſations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zenodorus</hi> alſo having his bowels burſt, through much blood that came from him, ended his life at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria;</hi> whereupon <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> gave his Tetrarchy to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod:</hi> he made him alſo one of the Governours of <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtill enlarged his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the reſt of the Governours of that Province, to do nothing without his advice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> beſtowed upon his Brother <hi>Pheroras</hi> a hundred Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of the revenues of his Kingdom, and begged a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarchy for him of <hi>Caeſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to the intent that if himſelf ſhould hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to dy, <hi>Pheroras</hi> eſtate might be ſecure, and not ſubject to <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> coming into the Eaſt, having ſetled his affairs there <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> conducted him to the Sea-ſide, and ſo returned into his own Kingdom, where he built a goodly Temple in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> all of white Marble, near to <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> built a Temple: and eaſed his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</note> at the foot of which mountain were the ſpring-heads of <hi>Jordan.</hi> He alſo remitted to his ſubjects ſome part of their Tribute, under pretence that he would eaſe them after the great dearth, but indeed to appeaſe the minds of his ſubjects,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40260:22"/> who were offended at his vaſt works, which ſeemed to tend to the deſtruction of Religion and good manners, as was commonly talked. As alſo to prevent theſe reports, he forbad all private meetings in the City, and to frequent Feaſtings:<note place="margin">His jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies.</note> He had ſpies alſo who would mingle themſelves in all companies, and mark what people ſaid: yea himſelf would go about in the night in the habit of a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and mingle himſelf in the company of people to hear what they thought of him: and ſuch as peremptorily diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his doings, he would puniſh without all mercy: the reſt of the multitude he bound to him by Oath, requiring that they ſhould not depart from their fidelity, and duty: Yea he required this Oath of many of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> as of <hi>Pollio,</hi> and <hi>Sameas,</hi> &amp;c. which though he could not get them to take, yet did he not puniſh them as he did others, in regard of that reſpect that he bore to <hi>Pollio:</hi> Neither did he impoſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Eſſeans,</hi> whom he much eſteemed for one <hi>Manaherus</hi> ſake, who was a Prophet, and when <hi>Herod</hi> was but a boy, he ſaluted him King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and foretold that he ſhould Reign above thirty years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> in the eighteenth year of his Reign, propounded to the <hi>Jews</hi> his building the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </note> whom when he ſaw troubled leaſt, when he had pulled down the old, he ſhould not be able to finiſh a new one, he told them, that the old Temple ſhould remain whole as it was, till all the materials neceſſary for the new Fabrick, ſhould be fully prepared: neither did he deceive them for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a thouſand wagons to carry ſtones, and he choſe out of all the Artificers ten thouſand that were the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite workmen, and a thouſand Prieſts, clothed in their Prieſtly garments at his coſt, who were not altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Maſons, and Carpenters Art, to overſee them.</p>
            <p>All neceſſary materials for this ſtately work being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in the ſpace of two years, <hi>Herod</hi> began to build the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> forty ſix years before the firſt Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the Miniſtry of Chriſt and therefore that text <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.20. ſhould be thus tranſlated, <hi>This Temple hath been built forty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40260:22"/> ſix years</hi> hitherto: So the learned Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and our Country-man <hi>Lydiat,</hi> read it,</p>
            <p>Indeed the building of the Temple under <hi>Zorobabel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the firſt year of the Monarchy of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and after ſome interruptions, was finiſhed in twenty years ſpace, <hi>viz.</hi> in the ſixth year of <hi>Dari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Hyſtaſpes:</hi> but the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent building of it, begun by <hi>Herod</hi> at this time was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in nine years ſpace and an half:<note place="margin">Nine years it was in building.</note> and truly the riches of <hi>Herod</hi> alone, were not ſufficient to perfect ſo magnificent a ſtructure, but all the holy treaſures of many ages, that were ſent to them from all the parts of the world to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> were ſpent about it.</p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Herod</hi> ſet ſail for <hi>Italy,</hi> to ſalute <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to ſee his Children at <hi>Rome,</hi> and as he paſſed through <hi>Greece,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He goes into <hi>Jtaly.</hi>
               </note> he was, not only preſent at, but Judg of the <hi>Olympick</hi> exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, where, obſerving that they did not anſwer the reſort that was to them, through the poverty of the <hi>Elienſes,</hi> he beſtowed towards them an yearly revenew, that ſo their Sacrifices might be made the more ſplendid, as alſo other things that tended to the gracing of ſo great a meeting: For which bounty he was declared perpetuall Judg of thoſe exerciſes.<note place="margin">His boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When he came to <hi>Rome, Caeſar</hi> intertained him courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and delivered to him his Sons ſufficiently inſtructed in the Liberal Sciences, and ſo from thence he went into <hi>Galatia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by the diligence of the Prieſts, the building of the Temple properly ſo called, that contained the Holy, and the Holy of Holies, was finiſhed in a year and an half; during which time, it is reported that it never rained in the day time, but only in the nights: and in the eight years fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, the Porches, the Ranges, and the reſt of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings about the Temple were all finiſhed.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> were returned into <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> and had gained all mens love, <hi>Salome</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Herod,</hi> and her Faction, fearing that at ſome time or other they would reveng their Mothers death, caſt out a rumour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, that they hated their Father, becauſe he had cauſed their Mother to be ſlain: But <hi>Herod</hi> as yet ſuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40260:23"/> no ill, uſed them with all Honour, as they deſerved: and becauſe they were now grown to mens eſtate, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided them Wives:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> Sons mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</note> for <hi>Alexander, Bernice,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Salome,</hi> and for <hi>Ariſtobulus, Glaphira,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> the King of the <hi>Cappadocians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>Herod</hi> hearing that <hi>Agrippa</hi> was again come into <hi>Aſia,</hi> he went to him, and begged of him that he would come into his Kingdom as to his Friend, and Gueſt; and as he came,<note place="margin">Herod <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertains</hi> Agrippa.</note> he entertained him in all the Cities that he had newly built, ſhewing him the publick buildings, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, both to himſelf and friends all kind of delights which might ſet forth his magnificence, at <hi>Sebaſte,</hi> and the Port of <hi>Caeſarca,</hi> and in the Caſtles of <hi>Alexandrion, Herodion,</hi> and <hi>Hyrcania.</hi> He brought him alſo into the City of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where all the People met him in their beſt, and Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall attire, and with acclamations of joy: <hi>Agrippa</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed an <hi>Hecatombe</hi> to God, and feaſted the People; and though he would willingly have ſtayed longer there, yet, fearing ſtorms, the Winter now drawing on, he haſted to ſail into <hi>Jonia,</hi> both he and his Friends having been honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with great preſents by <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Spring came, <hi>Herod</hi> hearing that <hi>Agrippa</hi> was going with an Army to <hi>Bosphorus,</hi> made haſt to meet him, and taking his way by <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and <hi>Chios,</hi> he came to <hi>Lesbos,</hi> thinking there to find him: But <hi>Agrippa</hi> being driven back by contrary North-winds <hi>Herod</hi> ſtaied at <hi>Chios,</hi> to whom many came privately to ſalute him, upon whom he beſtowed many princely gifts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> great bounty.</note> and when he perceived that the Gate of the City that was thrown down in the War againſt <hi>Methridates,</hi> as yet lay buryed in its ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins, and that by reaſon of the poverty of the Inhabitants, it could not by them be reſtored to its former beauty and greatneſs, he beſtowed upon them ſo much mony as would abundantly ſuffice to finiſh it, and exhorted them to haſten the reſtoring of their City to its former beauty, and grandure.</p>
            <p>As ſoon, as the wind ſerved, he left <hi>Chios,</hi> and ſailed to <hi>Mytilene,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Byzantium,</hi> and there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40260:23"/> that <hi>Agrippa</hi> had already paſſed the <hi>Cyanian</hi> Rock, he followed him with all ſpeed, and overtook him at <hi>Sinopi,</hi> a City in <hi>Pontus,</hi> where, beyond <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he arrived with his Navy: His coming was very grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him, and they embraced each other with ſingular affection,<note place="margin">His love to <hi>Agrippa</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Agrippa</hi> looking upon it as an evident argument of his fidelity and friendſhip, that leaving his manifold oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, he would come to him in ſo ſeaſonable a time. Wherefore <hi>Herod</hi> ſtill abode with him in the Army, was companion with him in his labors, and partaker of his counſels: He was alſo preſent with him when he went to be merry, and was the only man that he uſed in difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for the love that he bore unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agrippa</hi> having forced the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſphorans</hi> to lay down their Arms, in his whole journey thorough many countries and Cities, he gratified <hi>Herod</hi> in many things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Agrippaes</hi> love to him.</note> and at his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, relieved the neceſſities of many: If any one need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an interceſſor to <hi>Agrippa, Herod</hi> was the only man, by whom he could obtain his ſuit and aſſiſted many in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they had need of.</p>
            <p>When they were come into <hi>Jonia,</hi> a great multitude of <hi>Jews</hi> that inhabited that Country, complained of the great injuries that they ſuffered from the <hi>Jonians,</hi> who would not permit them to live after their own Laws, but that upon their Feſtivall days, they haled them before their Tribunals, and forbad them to ſend holy money to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which alſo they perverted to ſecular affairs, contrary to the priviledges granted them by the <hi>Romans:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Jonia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> took care that <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſhould hear their complaints, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them <hi>Nicholas Damaſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> one of his friends, to plead their cauſe, which when he had largely performed before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> (many honourable <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſome Kings and Princes being preſent) the <hi>Grecians</hi> denyed the thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing themſelves that the <hi>Jews</hi> were troubleſom to them: But they on the contrary proved that they were freeborn Citizens, and that they lived according to their own Laws without injuring of any; wherefore <hi>Agrippa</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that both for his friend <hi>Herod</hi>'s ſake, as alſo becauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40260:24"/> that which they demanded was juſt, he would gratifie them therein: He ordered therefore that the priviledges which were formerly granted them, ſhould remain invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, and that none ſhould moleſt them for living after their Country Laws. Then <hi>Herod</hi> roſe up, and gave him thanks in the name of them all: and ſo after mutuall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, they took their leave each of other, and departed from <hi>Lesbos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> in a few days after, having a proſperous gale, arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and from thence went to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where, calling all the people together,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gratiates him elf with the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </note> he gave them an account of his journey, and told them what immunities he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Aſia;</hi> and to win them the more to his friendſhip, he profeſſed that he would remit to them the fourth part of his Tribute; with which bounty they being exceedingly taken, wiſhed him all happineſs, and departed with great joy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Sons.</note>Preſently after his return, he was greatly incenſed by the falſe accuſations and artifices of his Siſter <hi>Salome,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Pheroras,</hi> againſt his two Sons that he had by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamne, Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus:</hi> whereupon to take down their ſpirits, he began to uſe them more hardly, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly he put hopes of the Kingdom into his Son <hi>Antipater,</hi> whom he begat when he was a private man, his Mother alſo being a woman of mean parentage, whom formerly he had baniſhed the City in favour to his two other Sons, and writing often unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> for him privately, he gave him great commendations: and at the intreaties of <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> he recalled alſo his Mother <hi>Doris,</hi> whom he had put away when he married <hi>Mariamne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He viſits <hi>Agrippa.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Agrippa</hi> afer his ten years Government in <hi>Aſia,</hi> being now to depart, <hi>Herod</hi> ſailed to ſalute him, taking with him of all his Sons only <hi>Antipater,</hi> whom he delivered to <hi>Agrippa</hi> with many gifts, to be carried to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to be brought into <hi>Caeſars</hi> favour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters</hi> ſubtilty.</note>
               <hi>Antipater</hi> was much honoured at <hi>Rome,</hi> being commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all his Friends by his Fathers letters: and though he was abſent, yet deſiſted he not by writing to incenſe his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40260:24"/> Father againſt the Sons of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> pretending his great care of his Fathers ſafety, but in truth, to make way for his ſucceſſion in the Kingdom. About this time <hi>Agrippa</hi> died, and being brought into the market place of <hi>Rome, Auguſtus</hi> commended him in a Funerall Oration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being now incenſed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt his Sons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth his Sons.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> he ſailed with them to <hi>Rome</hi> to accuſe them before <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and not finding him there, he followed him as far as <hi>Aquileia,</hi> before whom he accuſed them of treachery againſt him; but the young men ſatisfied all that were preſent by their Apology for themſelves mixed with prayers and tears, ſo that they were reconciled to their Father. After which, giveing thanks unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, and with them <hi>Antipater</hi> alſo, who pretended much joy that they were received into favour again.</p>
            <p>A few dayes after <hi>Herod</hi> gave <hi>Caeſar</hi> three hundred Talents,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſars</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note> and again <hi>Caeſar</hi> gave him half the revenues of the mettall Mines in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and the other half alſo he committed to his overſight, and having honoured him with other gifts of Hoſpitality, he gave him leave to chooſe which of his Sons he pleaſed to be his ſucceſſor, or if he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it better to divide his Kingdom amongſt them, which when he was about to do, <hi>Caeſar</hi> told him that he would not ſuffer but that he ſhould have his Kingdom during his life in his own power, as well as his Sons.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Herods</hi> abſence there was a rumour ſpread in <hi>Judea</hi> that he was dead, whereupon the <hi>Trachonites</hi> revolting, fell to their old trade of thieving; but by the diligence of his Captains that he had left in his Kingdom,<note place="margin">Thieves ſubdued.</note> they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and forty of the Chief of them, being terrified by the puniſhment of thoſe that were taken, left their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and fled into <hi>Arabia Nabathaea,</hi> where they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by <hi>Silaeus</hi> (who was an enemy to <hi>Herod,</hi> becauſe he had denyed him his ſiſter <hi>Salome</hi> to wife) who gave them a place to dwell in that was well fortified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> and his Sons ſailing homeward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with his Sons.</note> arrived at <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſte</hi> in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> where they met with <hi>Archelaus</hi> King of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> who courteouſly intertained <hi>Herod,</hi> much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40260:25"/> that his Sons were reconciled to him, and that <hi>Alexander</hi> had fairely anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red the crimes that were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt him: and ſo gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing royall gifts each to other, they parted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being returned into <hi>Judea,</hi> called the people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and told them what he had done in his voyage, and declared to them that his ſons ſhould reign after him, firſt <hi>Antipater,</hi> and then <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> that he had by <hi>Mariamne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time, in the year of the world 3994, <hi>Agrippa</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Jews</hi> of that name,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Agrippa</hi> born.</note> was born, who dyed when he was fifty four years old, being ſtruck by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.23. Alſo that lame man was now born, who being above forty years old, was healed by <hi>Peter,</hi> at the Beautifull gate of the Temple, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having finiſhed <hi>Caeſarea Stratonis</hi> in the twenty eighth year of his Reign, he dedicated it with great ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and many ſports and paſtimes: After which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build another Town in a field called <hi>Capharſala,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> great buildings.</note> which he called <hi>Antipatris,</hi> after his Fathers name; and a Caſtle alſo, which he called <hi>Cyprus</hi> after his Mothers name. In honour alſo of his dead brother, he built in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a very faire Tower, not inferiour to the <hi>Egyptian Pharos,</hi> and called it <hi>Phaſalus:</hi> and afterwards he built a Town of the ſame name in the valley of <hi>Jericho,</hi> from whence the country there about<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is called <hi>Phaſelus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having waſted his wealth by his great prodigality, and now wanting mony, after the example of <hi>John Hyrcanus,</hi> in the night,<note place="margin">He robs <hi>Davids</hi> Sepulchre</note> without the knowledge of the people, he opened <hi>Davids</hi> ſepulchre, where, though he found no mony, yet he found great ſtore of precious things, and ornaments of gold, which he took away: for the expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which fact, he afterwards built a moſt ſumptuous Monument of white Marble at the entrance of the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters</hi> ſubtilty.</note>
               <hi>Antipater,</hi> ſuborning other men falſly to accuſe his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> takes upon him their defence, that making a ſhew of good will to them, he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40260:25"/> might the eaſier oppreſs them: and by theſe ſubtilties he ſo wrought upon his Father, that thought him to be his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerver. Hereupon <hi>Herod</hi> commended his Steward <hi>Ptolomy</hi> unto <hi>Antipater,</hi> and communicated all his Counſels with his Mother <hi>Doris,</hi> ſo that all things were done as they pleaſed, and ſtill the King was imbittered againſt thoſe, whom it was their profit that he ſhould be angry with.</p>
            <p>About this time <hi>Pheroras (Herods</hi> Brother) fell ſo madly in love with his own ſervant, that he refuſed marriage with <hi>Cypros,</hi> the Kings Daughter, that was offered him by his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: He alſo accuſed <hi>Herod</hi> to his Son <hi>Alexander,</hi> as if he had been greatly in love with his Wife <hi>Glaphyra:</hi> for both which <hi>Herod</hi> was highly diſpleaſed with him.</p>
            <p>In the year of the world 3996, he began to be diſeaſed, who, lying at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> was after 38 years, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to health by Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> by the ſubtilties of his adverſaries,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> reconciled to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> being even driven to deſparation, was at this time reconciled to his Father by <hi>Archelaus,</hi> King of the <hi>Cappadocians,</hi> who came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to viſit <hi>Herod,</hi> and being accounted one of <hi>Herods</hi> chief Friends, received great gifts from him, and when he departed, <hi>Herod</hi> brought him as far as <hi>Antioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Herod</hi> went a third time to <hi>Rome</hi> to viſit <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in whoſe abſence thoſe Thieves of <hi>Trachonis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> goes again to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> whom <hi>Syllaeus</hi> had intertained, with their inrodes infeſted, not only <hi>Judea,</hi> but all <hi>Caeloſyria; Syllaeus</hi> affording them both impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>curity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> returned from <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns and dedicates the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> celebrated the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>le, reedified by him in the ſpace of nine years and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the very b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth day of his Kingdom, which he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ont to celebrate with great joy, at which time he Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ced unto God three hundred Oxen, and other of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red an innumerable company of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, every one according to his ability.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> finding that in his abſence his People had ſuſtained much dammage by thoſe Thieves of <hi>Trachonis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thieves do much miſchief.</note> and ſeeing he could not ſubdue them, being under the protection of the <hi>Arabian,</hi> he therefore entred <hi>Trachonis,</hi> and deſtroyed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40260:26"/> their Famelies, which yet did but incenſe them the more; ſo that, contemning all dangers, they moleſted <hi>Herods</hi> Countries with continuall excurſions, driving, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the peoples goods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod,</hi> hereupon ſent to the Preſidents of <hi>Syria, Saturninus,</hi> and <hi>Volumnius,</hi> deſiring that he might have the puniſhing of the Thieves of <hi>Trachonis,</hi> who by their incurſions had often waſted his Country. They, when they heard hereof, being increaſed to the number of a thouſand, began to waſte both fields, and villages, cutting the throats of all that fell into their hands; wherefore <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> demanded thoſe Thieves to be delivered over to him, and withall, required the ſixty Talents that he had lent <hi>Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>das</hi> upon <hi>Syllaeus</hi> his ſecurity, who had thruſt <hi>Obodas</hi> from the Government and now ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all himſelf: But <hi>Syllaeus</hi> denied that the Thieves were in <hi>Arabia,</hi> and deferred alſo to pay the money; whereupon the buſineſs was debated before <hi>Saturninus,</hi> and <hi>Volumnius,</hi> and in concluſion it was determined by them; that within thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes ſpace, both the money ſhould be repaid, and the runawayes of both Countries ſhould be delivered up, and <hi>Syllaeus</hi> ſwore by the <hi>Fortune</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi> before the Preſidents of <hi>Syria,</hi> that he would perform what was enjoyned.</p>
            <p>But when the time was expired, <hi>Syllaeus</hi> being unwilling to ſtand to the agreement, went to <hi>Rome:</hi> and in the mean time <hi>Herod,</hi> by the permiſſion of <hi>Saturninus,</hi> and <hi>Volumnius,</hi> to puniſh thoſe obſtinate people, raiſed an Army, entred <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia,</hi> and marched as far in three days as they uſed to do in ſeaven; and when he came to the Caſtle where the Thieves kept,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroies the Thieves.</note> he took it at the firſt aſſault, and demoliſhed a Fortreſs alſo called <hi>Raeeptu:</hi> and when a Captain of the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> came to their aid, they joyned battell, in which few of the <hi>Herodians</hi> were ſlain, but there dyed twenty five of the <hi>Arabians</hi> together with their Captain, whereupon the reſt fled. Being thus revenged of the Thieves, he brought three thouſand <hi>Idumaeans</hi> into <hi>Trachona,</hi> to reſtrain the thei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries committed there, and certified the <hi>Romane</hi> Generals, that he had only uſed that power which they had granted againſt thoſe obſtinate <hi>Arabians,</hi> which upon enquiry, they found to be true.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40260:26"/>
            <p>There were Letters poſted away to <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Syllaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</note> that related matters far otherwiſe, aggravating every thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their manner, by which Lyes <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſo much incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt <hi>Herod,</hi> that he wrote threatning Letters to him, becauſe he had marched with an Army out of his own Kingdom without his leave: and he was ſo far provoked, that he would not hear his Ambaſſadors, but diſmiſſed them without an anſwer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Trachanites,</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> taking hold of this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, moleſted the Garriſon of the <hi>Idumaeans</hi> that <hi>Herod</hi> had ſet over them; but <hi>Herod</hi> being affrighted with <hi>Caeſars</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, was fain to connive at it.</p>
            <p>About this time <hi>Obodas,</hi> King of <hi>Arabia Nabathaea</hi> dyed, and one <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſucceeded him, who changed his name into <hi>Aretas;</hi> which <hi>Syllaeus</hi> hearing of at <hi>Rome,</hi> endeavoured by falſe accuſations to have him thruſt from the Kingdom, and to get it to himſelf, beſtowing much money upon the Courtiers, and promiſing great things unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> whom he knew to be offended with <hi>Aretas,</hi> for aſſuming the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom without his conſent. In the mean while <hi>Aretas</hi> ſent Letters, and rich preſents unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and amongſt them a Crown worth many Talents: But <hi>Caeſar</hi> would not hear his Ambaſſadors, and ſcorned his Preſents, and diſmiſſed them without any thing done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being continually vexed with the inſolencies of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> ſent <hi>Nicholas Damaſcene</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> fals out with his Sons, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſons them.</note> if by the mediation of his Friends, he could get Juſtice from <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar:</hi> But in the mean time the diſcord with his Sons that he had by <hi>Mariamne,</hi> was greatly heightned by the artifices of <hi>Euri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hus</hi> a <hi>Laced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nian,</hi> which occaſioned <hi>Herod,</hi> to find out their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d treachery, to put to death by various torments, many both of his own, and of his Sons Friends, yet could he find no other evil by them, but ſome too free complaints of improvident young men, concerning their Fathers immoderate cruelty, and his too eaſie hearkning to baſe pick-thanks, of the wicked deceits of their Brother <hi>Antipater,</hi> and of the faction that was combined againſt them, and that, to free themſelves from theſe miſchiefs,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40260:27"/> they were ſaid to think of flying to <hi>Archelaus</hi> King of <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia,</hi> which thing indeed they did not deny: Hereupon <hi>Herod</hi> caſt them into priſon, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had been convicted of treaſon againſt their F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, reſolving to puniſh them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ff <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs went at <hi>Rome</hi> and concerning this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſent L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tters to <hi>Caeſ r</hi> by <hi>Volumnius,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and <hi>Olympius,</hi> his Friend.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Rome Nicholas Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcene</hi> joyned himſelf to the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> that cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to accuſe <hi>Syllaeus,</hi> profeſſing that he was his accuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r alſo before <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> and not <hi>Herods</hi> defender, and this he did, leſt he ſhould be repulſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d as others had been before him. When by this means he had gotten acceſs into <hi>Caeſars</hi> preſence, he indeed laid open many of <hi>Syllaeus</hi> his crimes, and withall added, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> was circumvented with his lies in the cauſe of <hi>Herod,</hi> which he confirmed by certain authentick records: This ſo prevailed with <hi>Caeſar</hi> that he condemned <hi>Syllaeus,</hi> and remanded him into the Province, that when he had ſatisfied the debt, he might be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> is reconciled to <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </note>From this time <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was reconciled to <hi>Aretas,</hi> and and <hi>Herod,</hi> and then received the Preſents that before he had ſo often rejected, and confirmed the Kingdom of the <hi>Arabians</hi> to <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tas.</hi> He adviſed <hi>Herod</hi> alſo by his letters, to call a Councel of his Friends at <hi>Berytus,</hi> and joyning the Preſidents of <hi>Syria,</hi> with <hi>Archelaus,</hi> the King of <hi>Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> by their joynt advice to determine of the buſineſs about his Sons.</p>
            <p>About this time the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> (who long before had foretold to <hi>Daniel</hi> the coming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> by a certain number of weeks) appeared at the right ſide of the Altar of incenſe to <hi>Zachary</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Angel appears to <hi>Zachary.</hi>
               </note> the Prieſt, of the courſe of <hi>Abia,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that there ſhould be born to him now in his old age, his wife <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zabeth</hi> alſo being well ſtricken in years and barren, a Son called <hi>John,</hi> a <hi>Nazarite,</hi> and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the Lord, in the ſpirit, and power of <hi>Elias:</hi> which he not believing was made dumb, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15, 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having received <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his letters, rejoyced exceedingly, both becauſe he was returned into his favour
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40260:27"/> and for that he had granted him power to do what he would with his Sons, and hereupon he convened by meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers all thoſe that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had appointed, to <hi>Berythus,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only <hi>Archelaus,</hi> and kept his ſons not far from the place, in a City of the <hi>Sidonians:</hi> and the Caſe being open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Saturninus,</hi> one that had been Conſul, delivered his opinion, but moderated with circumſtances, that <hi>Herods</hi> Sons were to be condemned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures his Sons to be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> but not to be put to death: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, his three Sons that were his Lieutenants, delivered their opinions to the ſame purpoſe: But <hi>Velumnius</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced that they were to be puniſhed with death, whoſe opinion the <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> part followed: and ſo the Councel being ended, <hi>Herod</hi> took his Sons with him, and meeting with <hi>Nicholas Damaſcene</hi> at <hi>Tyrus,</hi> they went together to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, when as a certain old Souldier named <hi>Tyro,</hi> had ſmartly reprehended <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty.</note> for his wickedneſs determined againſt his Sons, and told him that three hundred more of his Captains were of the ſame opinion, <hi>Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> commanded him to be caſt into priſon: <hi>Trypho</hi> the Kings Barber, taking this occaſion, accuſed <hi>Tiro</hi> for that he had often ſollicited him to cut the Kings throat with his razor, as he was trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and immediately both <hi>Tiro,</hi> and his Son, and the Barber were tortured: and <hi>Herod</hi> bringing thoſe three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Captains, and <hi>Tiro</hi> and his Son, and the Barber, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them before the People, againſt whom the people throwing any thing that came next to hand, ſlew them every one.</p>
            <p>Then were <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> led to <hi>Sebaſte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Sons ſtrangled.</note> and there ſtrangled by their Fathers command, and their bodies were buried in the Caſtle of <hi>Alex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndrian,</hi> where <hi>Alexander,</hi> their Grandfather by the mothers ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and many of their Prog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nitors, had been buried.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters.</hi> Treaſon.</note> when his Brethren were now dead, intended to remove his Father alſo out of the way: and knowing that he was hated by many in the Kingdom, he endeavoured by Bribes to get the good will of his Fathers Friends, both at <hi>Rome</hi> and in <hi>Judea;</hi> but eſpecially of <hi>Saturninus,</hi> the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40260:28"/> of <hi>Syria,</hi> and of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eroras,</hi> and <hi>Salome,</hi> the Brother and Siſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is time <hi>Herod</hi> ſent home <hi>Glaphira,</hi> the widdow of his ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>exander,</hi> to her F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>helaus</hi> the King of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wry out of his Treaſury, leſt ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>roverſie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> concerning it, and withall, he took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e young children of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tipa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> took very heavily, fearing leſt whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld come to age, they would hinder his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re their deſtruction: and he ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erod</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his flatteries that he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffered him to marry the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ughte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> and his ſon to marry the daug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cle <hi>Pheroras.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Herod</hi> invited <hi>Zamaris,</hi> a <hi>Babilonian Jew,</hi> and gave him a Country in <hi>Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>honis</hi> to inhabit, and this he did, that he might be a guard to that Country againſt Thieves: and <hi>Zamaris</hi> coming with five hundred Horſe, and an hundred of his kinſmen, erected Caſtles in divers places of that Country, by which means he ſecured the <hi>Jews</hi> that came from <hi>Babilon</hi> to the Feaſts at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from the Thieves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antipater</hi> working treaſon againſt his Father, drew in his Uncle <hi>Pheroras,</hi> and ſome of the Kings women, that were moſt addicted to the Sect of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the Phariſees.</note> except <hi>Salome,</hi> who conſtantly adhered to her Brother <hi>Herod.</hi> Theſe <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> were a crafty people, arrogant, and enemies to Kings, and they only of the whole nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> refuſed to ſwear allegiance to <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and were about ſix thouſand. For which cauſe <hi>Herod</hi> fined them, and the wife of <hi>Pheroras</hi> paid their fine for them, to whom, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, they foretold that the Kingdom ſhould be taken from <hi>Herod,</hi> and his children, and be transferred upon her Husband, and her, and their children: theſe things <hi>Salome</hi> made known to <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew ſome of them.</note> who examining the buſineſs, put ſome of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> to death, and with them, the Eunuch <hi>Dagoas,</hi> and his darling <hi>Carus,</hi> who was commended to him for his handſomeneſs; and beſides theſe, all the reſt of his Family whom he found to have conſpired with the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40260:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having puniſhed the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> called a Councill of his Friends, and before them began an accuſation againſt the wife of his brother <hi>Pherora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and when <hi>Pheroras,</hi> tho to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Brother, would not forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke her, he forbad <hi>Antipater Pheroras</hi> his company: and <hi>Antipater,</hi> that he might remove all ſuſpition from himſelf, procured by his friends that his Father ſhould ſend him immediately to <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> ſends his Son to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </note> ſent him with great preſents, and his <hi>Will,</hi> in which he declared that <hi>Antipater</hi> ſhould ſucceed him in the Kingdom: but if he died before him, then his Son that he had by <hi>Mariamus,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Simon</hi> the High Prieſt.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth moneth after <hi>John</hi> was conceived,<note place="margin">The Angel appears to <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </note> the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <hi>Gabriel</hi> was ſent to <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> to the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> betrothed to <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeph,</hi> of the ſame Tribe with her: <hi>viz.</hi> of the ſtock of <hi>David,</hi> and declared to her that ſhe ſhould bring forth the Son of God, and call his name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and ſhe being more fully taught of his admirable concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the power of the Holy Ghoſt overſhadowing her, with great Faith, ſaid, <hi>Be it to the handmaid of the Lord accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy word,</hi> Luk. 1.26, 38. and preſently after ſhe went into the Hill-Country, into a City of <hi>Judah</hi> (viz. <hi>Hebron,</hi> a City of the Prieſts, ſcituated in the mountains of <hi>Judea,</hi> Joſh. 21.10, 11.) where, when ſhe entred into the Houſe of <hi>Zachary,</hi> and ſaluted her Couſin <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the babe ſprang in her womb, and ſhe, being filled with the Holy Ghoſt, declared that <hi>Mary</hi> was bleſſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Luk. 1.39, 56.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> baniſhed his Brother<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> baniſhes his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>Pheroras</hi> into his <hi>Tetrarchy,</hi> becauſe he would not part with his wife, who ſwore that he would never return till he heard of <hi>Herods</hi> death, ſo that a little after, <hi>Herod</hi> falling ſick, and often ſending for him, to receive ſome private inſtructions, he refuſed to come for his oaths-ſake.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Elizabeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> time was come, ſhe brought forth a Son, who wa called <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt is born.</note> and <hi>Zacharies</hi> ſpeech being reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, he propheſied, ſaying, <hi>Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.57, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. and <hi>Joſeph</hi> finding his betrothed wife to be with child, thought of putting her away privily,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40260:29"/> but being warned by God in a dream, he took her to wife, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 1.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pheroras</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pheroras</hi> dieth.</note> falling ſick, and <hi>Herod,</hi> beyond expectation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, went to viſit him, and very kindly ſought help for him, but he died within a few dayes after, whoſe bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y was brought to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and interred by <hi>Herod,</hi> who honoured him with publick mourning.</p>
            <p>At this time two of <hi>Pheroras</hi>'s freed men, declared to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> how he was killed by poyſon, g ven him by <hi>Doris,</hi> the Mother of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tipater,</hi> which whileſt <hi>Herod</hi> enquired into, by little and little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e found out greater Villanies, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt treaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his Son <hi>Antip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters</hi> Treaſon.</note> who, when he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> had delivered a deadly poiſon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pheroras,</hi> that was ſent him out of <hi>Egypt</hi> from his Uncle <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heodore,</hi> the brother of <hi>Doris,</hi> wherewithall to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Father, that ſo the ſuſpition of the Parracide ſhould not lye upon him, being ſo far abſent.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Herod</hi> put <hi>Doris</hi> out of the Pallace, and took from her Jewels that were worth many Talents: He alſo put from him his wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> the daughter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh Prieſt, as a partner of all theſe ſecrets, and blotted h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſon out of his <hi>Will,</hi> and deprived her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather of the High Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſubſtituted in his room <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thias,</hi> the Son of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> that was born at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently after came <hi>Bathyllus, Antipaters</hi> freed-man from <hi>Rome,</hi> who being tortured, confeſſed that formerly he had brought poiſon, and given it to <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris,</hi> and <hi>Pher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ras,</hi> that if the firſt proved too weak, they ſhould be ſure to diſpatch <hi>Herod</hi> with the ſecond. There came alſo letters from his Friends at <hi>Rome,</hi> to the King, written by the entreaty of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters</hi> Craft.</note> in which <hi>Archelaus</hi> and <hi>Philip, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rods</hi> ſons, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for often complaining of the death of <hi>Alex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> pittying the misfortune of their murthered brethren: For theſe young men were ſtudying at <hi>Rome,</hi> and their Father had now commanded their return: whereupon <hi>Antipater</hi> by great gifts corrupted thoſe friends, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t by their letters they might make the young men ſuſpected to their Father, who if they lived, might be an hindrance to his hopes.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40260:29"/>
            <p>About this time <hi>Auguſtus</hi> taxing all the <hi>Roman</hi> world, our Lord Chriſt was born,<note place="margin">Chriſt is born.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Shortly after there came wiſe men from the Eaſt, the Star being their guide, to <hi>Herod</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught that the birth place of Chriſt, was <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> thither they went, and entring into the houſe, which was ſhewed them by the Star that ſtood over it, they found the Child, and fell down, and worſhipped him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mat. 2.1, 12.</p>
            <p>After the Angel of the Lord appeared unto <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeph</hi> in a dream, warning him to fly into <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> flies into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
               </note> where he remained till the death of <hi>Herod,</hi> Mat. 2.13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> thinking that the Child was ſtill at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> that he might deſtroy him amongſt the reſt, killed all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> kils the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> which were in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and in all the Coaſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from two years old, and under, according to the time (of the Star firſt ſeen in the Eaſt) that he had enquired of the wiſe men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> receiving letters from <hi>Antipater</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> in which he ſignified, that having diſpatched all his buſineſs according to his own mind, he would ſhortly return into his own Country, he wrote back to him again,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnares his Son.</note> diſſembling his anger, that he ſhould make haſt, leſt any thing ſhould befall him in his abſence that he ſhould not like of; and alſo gently complaining of his Mother, he promiſed that he would remit all differences after his return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antipater</hi> heard no news all this while either of the death of <hi>Phero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or of thoſe things that were on foot againſt him, though there were ſeven moneths ſpace between the wickedneſs proved againſt him, and his return.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipaters</hi> return.</note> For in his journey at <hi>Tarentum,</hi> he met with a letter of the death of <hi>Pheroras,</hi> and in <hi>Cilicia</hi> thoſe letters of his Father that called him back ſo haſtily; and when he came to <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenderis,</hi> a Town of <hi>Calicia,</hi> he began to doubt of his return, hearing of, and being extream ſorrowfull for the diſgrace of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet ſailing forwards, he came to <hi>Sebaſte,</hi> a Port of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rea,</hi> where, being ſaluted by none, he went to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40260:30"/>
            <p>It happened that <hi>Quintilius Varus,</hi> was the ſame time at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> being ſent as Succeſſor to <hi>Saturninus</hi> into <hi>Syria,</hi> and then called thither by <hi>Herod</hi> to aſſiſt him with his counſell in thoſe his weighty affairs. As they were ſitting both together, in comes <hi>Antipater</hi> not knowing any thing, and in his purple garment that he uſed to wear, entring the Pallace; but himſelf being entred, the Guards ſuffered none of his followers to come in with him: As he was coming near, his Father thruſt him from him, reproaching him with the murther of his Brethren, and his intention of poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning his Father, telling him that the next day <hi>Varus</hi> ſhould hear, and determine all things betwixt them, and accordingly the next day, <hi>Varu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the King, ſitting in Judgement, his Father himſelf firſt began the accuſation, and left the proſecution, and confirmation thereof to his old Friend, <hi>Nicholas Damaſcene,</hi> one that knew all the buſineſs, and when <hi>Antipater</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> accuſed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> could not clear himſelf from the crimes obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted againſt him, <hi>Varus</hi> commanded the poiſon that he had prepared for his Father to be brought forth, which being given to a condemned man, killed him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately: after which <hi>Varus</hi> roſe from the Council, and the next day went to <hi>Antiochia:</hi> but <hi>Herod</hi> caſt his Son into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſignified ſo much by letters to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> ſending alſo meſſengers, who by word of mouth might acquaint him with the curſed treaſon of <hi>Antipater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe meſſengers were poſting to <hi>Rome, Herod</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herods</hi> ſickneſs.</note> fell ſick, and made his <hi>Will,</hi> leaving his Kingdom to his young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Son, <hi>Herod Antipas,</hi> being exaſperated againſt his two elder Sons, <hi>Archelaus,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> by the falſe accuſations of <hi>Antipater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judas</hi> the ſon of <hi>Sariphaeus,</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galothus,</hi> two of the moſt learned of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and beſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the Law, knowing that the Kings ſickneſs was incurable, perſwaded ſome young men, that were their Scholars, to throw down the Golden Eagle<note place="margin">The Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Eagle hewn down.</note> that was ſet up by <hi>Herod,</hi> over the great gate of the Temple; who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, going up at noon day, pulled and hewed down with their axes the Eagle, a great multitude being in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40260:30"/> Temple, and beholding it: which as ſoon as it was told the Captain, he came with a ſtrong band of ſouldiers, and laid hold upon ſome forty of the young men, together with their Maſters, and brought them to <hi>Herod:</hi> Theſe conſtantly defending what they had done, <hi>Herod</hi> commanded them to be bound, and ſent them to <hi>Jericho:</hi> Then calling for the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> into whoſe Aſſembly he was brought in a Litter, by reaſon of his weakneſs, he complained to them, not ſo much of the injury done to himſelf, as to God (as he ſaid) Theſe denying that it was done by their order, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what pacified him, only he took away the High Prieſthood from <hi>Matthias,</hi> whom he ſuſpected not to be a ſtranger to that fact, and made his ſucceſſor <hi>Jazer,</hi> the Brother of his Wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Simon</hi> the High Prieſt; but he burned alive the other <hi>Matthias</hi> that was the author of this ſedition, and his companions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herods</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod</hi> puts them to death. His ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth.</note> diſeaſe began now to grow worſe: for he was burned with a ſlow fire, which was not perceived ſo much by the outward touch, as by the inward effects of it, which burnt up his very bowels: He had alſo the diſeaſe called the <hi>Bulemia,</hi> or Dog-like appetite, which provoked him to a continuall deſire of eating, and yet nothing would ſatisfie him: He was alſo continually tormented with ulcers in his bowels, and pains of the collick: His feet ſwelled with a moiſt phlegm, and his thighs alſo: His members rotted and were full of worms, which occaſioned an intollerable ſtink: He was no leſs troubled with a <hi>Priapiſme:</hi> and moreover was vexed with grievous convulſions, and difficulty of breathing.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough he was ſo grievouſly tormented, that every one judged that he could not be able to endure it long,<note place="margin">All means of cure fail him.</note> yet he hoped that he ſhould break through it, being very carefull to ſend for the ableſt <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and ſought medecines from every place: He went alſo beyond <hi>Jordan</hi> to the hot Baths at <hi>Calli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> which run into the <hi>Asphaltite</hi> lake, which beſides the medeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal vertue, are pleaſant, and good to be drunk: There being, by the advice of his <hi>Phyſicians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſet into a bathing tub of oil, he ſeemed to them to be giving up the Ghoſt, yet by the ſudden crying out, and lamentations of his Friends, he came to himſelf again, and now ſeeing no hope of recovery, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded fifty <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aes</hi> to be given to every ſouldier, and having ſhewed much liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity to his Captains, and Friends, he returned again to <hi>Jericho.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40260:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> being told that amongſt the children which <hi>Herod</hi> had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſlain at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thlehem,</hi> there was a ſon alſo of his own ſlain, He ſaid, <hi>That it was better to be</hi> Herods <hi>hog than his Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> by an edict called together to <hi>Jericho,</hi> all the moſt Noble of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and when they came, he ſhut them all up together in a place called, the <hi>Hippodrome,</hi> giving command to his ſiſter <hi>Salome,</hi> and her huſband <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexus,</hi> that as ſoon as he was dead, they ſhould cauſe his ſouldiers to ſlay them all,<note place="margin">His cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> that ſo the people might have cauſe of ſorrow, who otherwiſe (he feared) would rejoyce at his death.</p>
               <p>At this time letters came from <hi>Rome</hi> from the Ambaſſadors whom he had ſent to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> wherein they certified him that the Emperor left <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater</hi> to his Fathers pleaſure, either to baniſh, or to put him to death. <hi>Herod</hi> hearing this, was a little cheared: but preſently his torments returning, and being greedy of mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he called for an apple and a knife to pare it, intending with the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife to have ſtabbed himſelf,<note place="margin">He at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to murther himſelf.</note> which alſo he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tempted: but <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus,</hi> his Nephew, prevented him, and holding his right hand, called for help. This accident cauſed much ſorrow, fear, and tumult through the whole Pallace, as if <hi>Herod</hi> had been dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antipate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> perceiving the noiſe, thought verily that his Father was dead, and thereupon begin to tamper with his Keeper about letting him out, promiſing him great rewards, both for the preſent, and for the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure when it would lye in his power amply to reward him: This his practice the Keeper told to the King, who for indignation cryed, and though he was ſo near death, yet did he raiſe up himſelf on his Bed, and commanded o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of his Guard to go preſently and kill <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pater,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antipater</hi> ſlain. <hi>Herods</hi> Will.</note> and to bury him in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>canion</hi> without any honour, which was done accordingly.</p>
               <p>Then did he make a new Teſtament: for <hi>Antipas,</hi> whom before he had made ſucceſſor to his Kingdom, he made <hi>Tetrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> of <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lee,</hi> and <hi>Petre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> To his ſon <hi>Philip</hi> he aſſigned the regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns of <hi>Gaulanitis, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitis, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> and <hi>Pancada</hi> in the name of a Tetrarchy, but he gave the Kingdom to his Son <hi>Archelaus:</hi> To his ſiſter <hi>Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me</hi> he gave <hi>Jamnia, Az<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tus,</hi> and <hi>Thaſaelis,</hi> with five hundred thouſand <hi>Dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hmaes:</hi> To the reſt of his kindred he gave money, and yearly Penſions. To <hi>Cae a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> he gave ten Millions of <hi>Drach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes</hi> of ſilver, and all his Plate, as well of Gold as of Silver, and a great quantity of precious moveables: and To <hi>Livia, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſars</hi> wife, and ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain friends, he gave five Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions of <hi>Dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hmaes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus ordered theſe things, five dayes after <hi>Antipater</hi> was put to death,<note place="margin">His Death</note> he dyed himſelf, having enioyed the Kingdom 34 years after the death of <hi>Antigonus:</hi> but from the time that he was declared King by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> 37 years, about the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of our <hi>November,</hi> in the year of the world 4001, and after the birth of Chriſt, about two years.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>
               <hi>There is lately publiſhed by</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sam Clarke, <hi>a new Piece of Lives, containing the Lives of ten Eminent Divines, with ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther private Chriſtians, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines being as follow;</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Carter, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sam Crook, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Cotton, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tho. Hill, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Will. Gouge, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tho. Gataker, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jeremy Whitaker, <hi>A.</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> James Uſher, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rich. Capel, <hi>and</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rob. Harris, <hi>&amp;c. Sold by</hi> Will. Miller <hi>at the Gilded Acorn near the Little North Door in</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
